<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of romanizing recusants, and dissembling Catholicks. A counter-maund of a counterfeit embassage. Or, An answer to the posthume pamphlet of Ralfe Buckland sometime a popish priest secretly printed and published after his death about a yeere a goe.</title>
            <author>Sanderson, Thomas, 1560 or 61-1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21711</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114100</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849328</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849328</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14468</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14468)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1494:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of romanizing recusants, and dissembling Catholicks. A counter-maund of a counterfeit embassage. Or, An answer to the posthume pamphlet of Ralfe Buckland sometime a popish priest secretly printed and published after his death about a yeere a goe.</title>
                  <author>Sanderson, Thomas, 1560 or 61-1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 99, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Purfoot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Th. Sanderson.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Buckland, Ralph, 1564-1611. --  Embassage from heaven --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14468:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14468:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OF ROMANIZING <hi>RECVSANTS,</hi> AND DISSEMBLING CATHOLICKS. A COVNTER-MAVND <hi>of a counterfeit Embaſſage.</hi> OR, <hi>AN ANSWERE TO the poſthume Pamphlet of</hi> Ralfe Buckland <hi>ſometime a Popiſh Prieſt, ſecretly printed and publiſhed</hi> after his death about a yeere a goe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>I haue not ſent theſe Prophets ſayth the Lord, yet they ranne: I haue not ſpoken to them, yet they Prophecied.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ieremy. 23.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON. <hi>Printed by Thomas Purfoot.</hi> An. Dom. 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:14468:2"/>
            <head>Theſe things are performed in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> THe ſcope or drift of the Prieſts Pamphlet is iuſtified. (viz.) That diſsembling Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in <hi>England</hi> ought to vnmaske themſelues.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The Popiſh Doctrine inſerted, is controwled by the Poſitiue Doctrine of Truth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The prophane blaſphemies and vniuſt Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations against the true profeſsours cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Protestants, are iuſtly retorted vpon the Popiſh Synagogue.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Vnſetled Conſciences among the Papiſts, are exhorted to continew their obedience to the proceedings of the Engliſh Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Church, that by gods grace in the end they may be ſetled in the Truth.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14468:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE MOST REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, the Lord</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> his Grace, Primate and Metropolitane of all <hi>England;</hi> and of his Maieſties most Honourable priuie Councell; my very good Lord.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most Reuerend Father:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE DEDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of euery work framed againſt the Common Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our Church and State, ſeemeth vnto me of right, next vnder his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, to belong vnto your Grace, in regard both of your Place, and Perſon. Your Place being as that of <hi>Zadock,</hi> or <hi>Nathan,</hi> to King <hi>Dauid:</hi> your Perſon worthy of all Honour.
<pb facs="tcp:14468:3"/> Whome God and the King haue ſo greatly honoured with ſuch high and eminent gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and endowments; as which, truly, none, ſaue Haereticall and Prophane Spirits of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy and malignitie, can dis-taſt; but which the syncerely-chriſtian ought to proſecute with all Honourable approbation and loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The conſideration whereof, reſpectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joyned with ſome other congruent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, hath emboldned me, at this time, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misly to entreat your Graces Patronage of this my firſt Onſet, in this Kind, which I haue giuen to the Ieſuiticall Oppoſite. Wherefore in all humilitie preſuming to commend the ſame to your Graces protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I pray God almighty to aſſiſt and bleſſe your Grace, in all your weighty affaires, with his moſt holy Spirit, and happy ſucces for euer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces in all moſt humble affection, and duty. <hi>TH. SANDERSON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14468:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader: In this Treatiſe, Truth and zeale of Gods glory which were aymed at, I truſt, will appeare. But I ſhould hardly haue deliuered ſtore of reading, though I had beene furniſhed therewith. For neither doth the quality of the Meſſage controwled, require it: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it fitting for him in whoſe name it is anſwered, to make ſhew of it. The Perſon anſwering is our bleſsed Sauiour himſelfe, whoſe word is a proofe inuincible. In whoſe name a popiſh Prieſt hath audaciouſly praeſumed to deliuer an Embaſsage which he neuer receaued. The Meſſage it ſelfe is full of rayling, lyes, and blaſphemies; but no learning at all. I cannot find that ſcarcely once he attempteth to prooue any of thoſe idolatrous and Popiſh opinions, which he euery where ſcattereth. As he lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth downe falſe principles of Popiſh doctrine without proofes: ſo it may be found in this <hi>Countermand,</hi> that they are croſsed and checked with the Poſitiue Truth, ſupported with ſome chiefe &amp; fundamentall arguments thereof. Of this I thought good to aduertiſe thee, becauſe this Anſwere intendeth onely to diſcouer the praeſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a falſe Embaſsadour, the impudent calumniations of a notable Rayler, and the erroneous doctrines of a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh
<pb facs="tcp:14468:4"/> Prieſt: to the end, to controwle the malapert ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines of the Embaſſadour, to retort the iniurious crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the Railer, to oppoſe the Truth of God to the Romiſh profeſsion; that wiſedome may be iuſtified of all her children; and they that run well may run ſo ſtill, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the light of God do ſhine full in their hearts: and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till vnremooueable grace bee with all them that loue the Lord Ieſus Christ in ſyncerity.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:14468:4"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Short Horſe is ſoone curried; though a ragged Colt is not ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denlie broken. A pettie pamphlet may be ſodenlie anſwered; though a prophane pedantick <hi>Haeretick</hi> is not ſo readily put to ſilence. But it is no matter: Dogs will barke; and euill wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers will euer be buſie bodies? and the Conciſion will neuer bee of the true circumciſion. <hi>Si pro er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore homines &amp; damnabili diſsenſione, &amp; conuicta modis omnibus falſitate tanta praeſumunt, &amp;c. quantò magis aequum eſt, &amp; oportet eos qui pacis &amp; vnitatis Chriſtianae aſſerunt veritatem &amp;c. ſata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere inſtanter at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> impigrè, non ſolum pro eorum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimine quiiam catholici ſunt, verum etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro eorum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectione qui nondum ſunt? Nam ſipertinacia inſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles vires habere conatur, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tas debet habere conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,<note place="margin">Aug. ad Feſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ep. 197.</note> quae in eo bono quod perſeuerantèr &amp; infatigabilitèr agit, &amp; Deo placere ſe nouit, &amp; proculdubio non poteſt hominibus prudentibus diſplicere?</hi> It is therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, and it ſhall not be grieuous, becauſe it is a work of no great labour, as to anſwere words with words againe; <hi>a foole according to his follie, &amp;c:</hi> ſo to teach a yong coltiſh Prieſt, by this Prieſt, to range a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb facs="tcp:14468:5"/> without an errand; and pretend an Embaſſage without a meſſage. Whoſe ragged
<hi>Rhetorick,</hi> &amp; jm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t boldnes is the more jntolerable, becauſe he taketh vpon him the perſon of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> hauing been himſelfe a <hi>Prieſt</hi> &amp; lym of Antichriſt: &amp; hauing crept like a <hi>Locuſt</hi> out of the bottomleſſe pit; he crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth himſelfe the king of kings and Lord of Lords as comming downe from heauen. Is it any matter to halter the necks and euen to breake the hearts of ſuch Colts? Who dare to entitle their owne beaſtlie and blaſphemous neighings with the name of, <hi>An Embaſsage from the ſonne of God, our Lord and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt?</hi> But becauſe this Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor is now departed the mortalitie of this life, as it ſeemeth to be inſinuated in the preface, I leaue him to the Iudgement of the Eternall Iudge:<note place="margin">Auguſtinus.</note> whoſe Iudgements are ſometimes manifeſt, ſometimes ſecret, alwaies iuſt. Neuer-theleſſe as one of the <hi>Lords Prophets</hi> and ſervants of Chriſt, in the cauſe. and quarrell of my Maiſter though the meaneſt and weakeſt of Ten-thouſand I haue thought good to take in hand from a true and harty zeale that I beare vnto the Church of Chriſt, to examine this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage. And firſt he might haue gyuen leaue to ſome ſturdier ſteed to haue ruſhed into the battell formoſt, whether his meaning were in ſimple ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie to call backe his friends from the Enemies campe; or in ſlye ſubtiltie to ſtirre and raiſe vp an open Rebellion: ſo to muſter all the papiſts in this Kingdome: (Recuſants and
<hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe diuideth them) in one <hi>Armie.</hi> I will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine

<pb facs="tcp:14468:5"/> his meaning, becauſe I know not his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, I leaue the purpoſe of his heart to him that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But (as one ſaith) <hi>Quicquid id eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virg. AEneid. 2. Prov. 12.5.</note> 
               <hi>timeo.</hi> I feare whatſoeuer it be. For I am ſure: <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilia impiorum ſunt fraudulenta.</hi> The counſels of the vngodly are deceitfull.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>An evill Tree cannot bring foorth good fruit:</hi> and a bad man can hardly haue a good meaning: (as the Lord ſaid to the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes):<note place="margin">Mat. 12.34.</note> 
               <hi>How can yee ſpeake good things when yee your ſelues are euill?</hi> Wee will not doubt but the Ieſuited Recuſant is in his hart traitourouſly affected: and waiteth onely for an oportunitie to be a Rebell. When time and power ſhould haue offered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues we make no queſtion but Captaine <hi>Buckland,</hi> Prieſt, would haue buckled vp himſelfe and his harneſſe to the battell; and ſo will all that are of his minde, to roote out the memoriall of Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, though it be by faggot and fier, or famine, or Sword, or any other violent &amp; forcible meanes. But thanks be to God, we hope, that long deſired black and bloudy day dawneth not yet, howſoeuer their many brauadoes and cracking threats may make perhaps ſome peoples harts, of the weaker ſort amongſt vs, to ſtartle now and then within them. A little puffe of a quick winde will eaſely raiſe a ſmall billow in euery Riuer, yet no danger of a ſtorme at all. And therefore not troubling our ſelues greatly with this pettie Captaines purpoſe: though it were, as it may ſeeme it was, in this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage, to ſtrike vp an Alarum to an ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rebellion of the Popiſh faction: but truſting in him that kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth
<pb facs="tcp:14468:6"/> 
               <hi>Iſraell</hi> neither ſlumbring nor ſleeping:<note place="margin">Pſal
121.4.</note> wee leaue his jmagined deuice and drift vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his aſſociats, to diſcloze or Cloze vp in their owne boſomes at their owne pleaſure. Only this wee aduiſe his (ſo named by him) Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks: that becauſe they are Papiſts, they would Correct their opinions, and becauſe no Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks in Ioyning with our Church, they would hold on their practiſe: It may in time by Gods grace, and good means, reforme their hypocriſie and diſſimulation wherewith they are charged, whether Iuſtly or vniuſtlye, themſelues can tell beſt, by this Prieſt. Yf they haue a good meaning and are comming onwards to the true Chriſtian faith, they are in a right courſe to Ioyne with vs in our ſeruice and Churches. If they ſtand reſolute as yet in their ſuperſtitious deuotion: Yet God may reueale the better parte vnto them. If they be obſtinate both <hi>Haereticks</hi> and <hi>Hypocrits,</hi> and corrupt our people with their leven of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Creeping into corners ſeduce the hearts of the ſimple; either let them hearken vnto their owne prieſt; or els, <hi>Vtinam abſcindantur qui perturbant nos.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 5.12.</note> Would to God they were cut of that trouble vs. And ſo I come to the Embaſſage. Wherein not to trouble our ſelues at all with his method, beeing, as I conceaue it, nothing els but a bundell of goodly argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts heaped together to perſwade <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> diſſembling papiſts to become open and obſtinate Recuſants: (That only concluſion being the drift of his whole meſſage:) Let vs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
<pb facs="tcp:14468:6"/> him foote by foote; and as he nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth them vp in order, and ſo prawnceth forward in his run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vaine and Rhetoricall trappings: ſo let vs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the fowle and daungerous bogs of filthy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh way wherouer he trippeth like a wilde Iriſh: and, as it ſeems, would haue our Proteſtants who may light vppon his booke, to runne and fall, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnacquainted with ſuch paths and Paſſages. Wherefore our Cheife purpoſe is onlie to diſcouer thoſe erroneous and Blaſphemous Poſitions and Paradoxes which here and there he hath tumbled into his Treatiſe: whereinto whoſoeuer ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him of the Proteſtant flocke may plunge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as into popiſh and Impious bogs and gulfes before they be aware. The reſt of his Rhetoricke tending only to the perſwaſion of their Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall Crew to vnmaſke themſelues and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in outward profeſſion that which they are in inward reſolution. We let Paſſe, as it were, as not offenſiue vnto vs: wiſhing, as well as he, that no one of them would diſſemble with God and the world, but ſhew themſelues in their owne colours that we might know by their pronunciation whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be <hi>Gileadits</hi> or
<hi>Ephraimits?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 22.5.6.</note> on our parts, or on our enemies. For if wee ſhall finde them hereafter to be onely <hi>Temporizers,</hi> Cunning <hi>Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auels, vnderminers, Vault-workers,</hi> or the like becauſe they are in opinion halting
<hi>Iſraelites,</hi> halfe-baked <hi>Ephraimits,</hi> luke warme <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> and the like: wee ſhall hold it, I truſt, a moſt iuſt and neceſſarie courſe to cut them of for notorious <hi>Hypocrits</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:14468:7"/> God, &amp; detected Traitors againſt their King and country. Laſtlie, becauſe this falſe Embaſſador hath been ſo bold to deliuer this Meſſage in the name of Chriſt; wee hauing greater reaſon in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the verie truth, then he had of his Popiſh cauſe, to craue the aſſiſtance of our bleſſed <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Sauiour:</hi> doe moſt humbly intreat his heauenly Maieſtie to Countermaund this Embaſſage as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forged in his name, &amp; to controwle the follies, falſhoods, and blaſphemies thereof, in his owne words: Humbly crauing pardon of his Highnes, &amp; Holines, being moſt vnworthy to ſpeake from ſo great &amp; abſolute a Monarch, though wee ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the meſſage with no ſemblable wiſedome, inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie, and perfection as may beſeeme ſo diuine a Maieſtie. Therefore thus we proceed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="extract">
            <pb facs="tcp:14468:7"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE TO ALL Schiſmaticks.</head>
            <p>TO you, oh you miſerable, who ſtraying from the pathes of peace, runne as confidently forwards in darke and ſlipperie waies, as if yee traced the ſteppes of truth and righteouſneſse, neither wandred one iot from the high way to ſalvation.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>AN ANSWERE TO the Epistle;</head>
               <p>OR rather to the Title: if it be ſo much.<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ax faucibus haeret. Manum de ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula?</note> For mee thinkes his tongue cleaueth to the roofe of his mouth. Hath he taken ſo ſoone and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly his hand from the worke? what is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? doth griefe thrattle him, &amp; his ſpirit burne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him? either doth his memorie forſake him? or his heart ſmite him? Cannot <hi>Balaam</hi> vtter his para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe God will not giue him leaue to curſe his people? what motion? what paſsion is this? what Lethargie? what Apoplexie poſſeſſed the braine of this Prieſt, that beginning a ſentence, hee was not able to bring it forth. Belike the Diuell ought him a fowle ſhame, to trip him downe on the threſhold: &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:14468:8"/> cut off both his head and his hands here; for both his wit and his fingers faild him in this entrance. Or was it not the Angell of the Lord of hoaſts that ſtood in <hi>Balaams</hi> way to forbid him? nay, to rebuke and controwle his conſcience in this wicked courſe and Treatiſe; and yet to ſuffer him to go on forward withall. Chriſtian Reader, marke I pray you, if this be not very memorable, that this falſe Embaſſador is made to ſpeake, and not to ſpeake: to begin, and not to make an end, like a cravin Cocke that begins to crowe, and ſtops vpon a ſodaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To you, oh you miſerable, &amp;c.</hi> What doth hee ſay to them? Nay: that is abrupted, either by the failing of his memorie, or by the feeling of his conſcience: or by both. As he that came vpon the Stage, when he had ſaid <hi>(Vtinam ne in nemore)</hi> was able to go no farther: ſo this praun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Prieſt directing an Epiſtle to all Schiſmaticks, meaning, his Catholique minded that come to our Churches, beginning at firſt more like a franticke &amp; furious Herauld, then a ſober &amp; prudent Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor to rayle at them, is choked as it wereof him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as chaſing and cholerick ſpirits vſe to bee in their overhaſty fumes, not able to deliuer one perfect Period. But <hi>A Domino factum eſt istud,</hi> this was the Lords doing, that he became ſo ſpeechleſſe vppon a ſodaine.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ob. 38.11.</note> He that ſaid to the Sea,
<hi>hitherto ſhalt thou come, and here ſhall it ſtay thy proude waues;</hi> gaue a notable forewarning to this blaſphemer, hitherto to range, &amp; here to breake off his prowde words: if
<pb facs="tcp:14468:8"/> he had had the grace to take it. But as it is our ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred corruption to like beſt, and bee moſt eager of the forbidden fruite: and as the Poet ſpake of a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackfull jade,
<q>
                     <l>The more he was held in with Bridle and bit,<note place="margin">Vidi ego nuper equum contra ſua froena te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacem, Ore reluctanti fulminis tre modo. <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>The more head-ſtrong &amp; furious he ſtroue againſt it.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And as a ſtrong Current the more it is ſtopped, the more it rageth till it runne over the banks, like the ſwelling of <hi>Iordan:</hi> ſo it is apparant that this naughty nature would not be warned, this vnbride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Pegaſus</hi> would not bee tamed, this running Rhetorician would not be reſtrained; but his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble tongue muſt needs caſt out the wilde fire of blaſphemies againſt CHRIST and his truth: of ſlaunders againſt the Goſpell, and Profeſſours thereof: and of revilings againſt his owne Catholique minded, as in the ſequele wee ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14468:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14468:9"/>
            <head>THE COVNTERMAVND of the counterfait EMBASSAGE.</head>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>HEarken yee erring ſoules who will not enter the Arke ordained for the ſafety of my elect:<note place="margin">The dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes.</note> yet hope, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Come forth before me and iuſtifie your ſelues if yee can, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To all both Angels and Men, I appeale to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes and Heretickes, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>EARKEN YEE</hi> FALSE Embaſſadors and meſſengers of the Romane harlot. Yee runne, but I ſend you not: yee ſpeake, but I haue not ſpoken vnto you: your diſſembling Catholiques I doe not iuſtifie, either in their opinions, or in their diſſimulations. Their opinions are haereticall, their diſſimulation is damnable:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14468:10"/> yet their ſuting and ſorting with my Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in <hi>England</hi> is both juſtifiable in it ſelfe, and acceptable vnto me. Their eſtate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is not herein dangerous: never trouble them with ſuch account. But yours, who are Recuſants, is. For in your own words to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere you. Ye are <hi>the erring ſoules</hi> who <hi>will not enter the Arke:</hi> nor <hi>refuſe to leaue Sodome:</hi> who <hi>forſake not the Tabernacles of Korah:</hi> who <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to flye from Babylon:</hi> yee are the <hi>lost ſheepe</hi> who have worne out <hi>My marke, and enter an other folde:</hi> yee <hi>runne with the theefe, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with iniquity:</hi> yee <hi>broken braunches igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of your owne decay:</hi> yee <hi>rent my vnſeamed coate:</hi> yee <hi>teare my bodie:</hi> yee <hi>breake the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of my Church without ſcruple of Schiſme.</hi> Could you poſſibly have deuiſed fitter words wherein to deſcribe your own <hi>Hereticall</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> qualities? Therefore ſtand vp and plead for your ſelues if you bee able be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me your Iudge, and <hi>Creator of all:</hi> your wickedneſſe ſhall teſtifie vnto your owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and let <hi>all my Creatures</hi> teſtifie againſt you for notorious <hi>Impoſtors; Men</hi> and <hi>Angels; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> and <hi>Romaniſts; Christians</hi> and <hi>Infidels;</hi> and <hi>your owne Conſciences, if yee haue any.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14468:10"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>I Haue tryed you and found you faithleſse, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks no true ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of GOD.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I haue prouided for you a plentifull haruest of glorious and eternall merits, I proffer the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of the kingdome of Heauen, but I perceiue, &amp;c. Oh ſeed of <hi>Samaria,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Lord Christ.</head>
                  <p>YOu I haue tryed and found, indeed, a faithles and diſloyall generation: yee haue ſet at naught my wiſedome and bountie, and contemned the treaſures of my kingdome. Oh yee ſeed of
<hi>Samaria,</hi> your idolatrous blindnes and frowardnes, as that of vntamed <hi>Ephraim,</hi> I deteſt, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horr, and cannot digeſt. The purchaſe of the kingdome of Heaven by my glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and aeternall merits, how ſo ever I ſeeme to proffer vnto all, yet I have provided for none but my true beleevers. As for them, who only for the feare of a Temporall loſſe, will not make publique and open profeſſion of the truth, how can I chooſe but hate their ſo daſtardlie diſſimulation? Yet I am no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14468:11"/> Counſellor, as thou wouldeſt make me here, Oh thou falſe tongue, to any vnreſolved or vnſetled ſoules, to turne Traytors to their King and Countrey, to the hazard of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir liues and goods.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vngra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and their iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dealing towards GOD.</note>IF any man with-hold your right, an action is readie, he is ſerued with proceſse and exclaimed against for vnconſcionable dealing, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But where is your owne dutie? the honour of your Maker, the loue of your Redeemer, the awe of your God? where are the fruites which my care haue deſerued? Long haue I trauailed in manuring your barren ſoules: I haue ſent my labourers, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>TVrne your eyes and looke vppon your ſelves yee Runnagates, and yee ſhall ſee that yee are the men of vnthankefulnes here deſcribed. I will and do challenge you in your owne words, that you with-hold your owne ſoules from me my right and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14468:11"/> by Purchaſe of redemption: that you are ſtubborne ſervants and diſobedient Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: that <hi>I haue ſent my labourers</hi> vnto you: who haue
<hi>travailed</hi> much with him: that <hi>I haue by many occaſions ſollicited</hi> you:<note place="margin">Recuſant Papiſts ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes ſollicited to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ome to the truth of the Ghoſpell prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ted in England.</note> as by the great proſperitie and long peace of this Land, by miraculous defence of the late Queene, and the preſent King thereof, and ſtrange deliverances of all the ſtates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, both from forraine invaſions, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall treaſons, ſecret, and open practiſes: by encreaſing both the multitude and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my true Paſtors according to my mind, <hi>as I promiſed of old vnto my Church,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ierem. 3.15</note> and many other vnſpeakeable bleſſings beſides: yet have you like <hi>barraine ſoules</hi> brought foorth no ſweet and kindly fruites of truth and Godlines, but <hi>vnprofitable</hi> and bitter weeds of Poperie and Impietie. <hi>Stiff and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractable</hi> as yee are; <hi>wicked and perverſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> why doe yee wrong <hi>my patience?</hi> and
<hi>dailie vexe me</hi> to drawe my people from me? yea thoſe among yourſelves that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming towards me? <hi>why doe yee your ſelues thus forſake me, and deny me? deſpize and diſobey me? oppugne and aſsault me?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14468:12"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks deny, deſpiſe, and impugne GOD.</note>YEE forſake me and deny mee, and ſay with a bold countenance wherein haue wee forſaken and denied thee? Haue yee not renounced my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice? caſt off my liuerie? departed from my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie? Haue not I ordained Sacraments for your ſpeciall comfort? A Sacrifice, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>HEre you lay vpon your friends a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold accuſation in my name: but I haue not accuſed them of <hi>Deniall, Contempt,</hi> and <hi>Reſiſtance of God</hi> in yeelding <hi>to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of a Proteſtant.</hi> Your ſervice is not my <hi>ſeruice,</hi> your Coate my
<hi>liuerie,</hi> your Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue my <hi>familie,</hi> your pitcht field my <hi>Campe and Colours;</hi> or the Proteſtants pavilions mine <hi>Aduerſaries Tents:</hi> yee are my Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and your Tents are the tents of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlines, your Campe and Colours are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite vnto mine. To enter your familie, to weare your liverie, to doe ſervice in your aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies is to forſake and denie mine. But they doe well that doe the contrarie. Againe, I haue
<hi>Commanded</hi> all my profeſſors <hi>to loue mee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14468:12"/> aboue all, to confeſse my Name,</hi> my faith, and Church, and to ſtriue for the truth even vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bloud. But your Religion is not the <hi>Truth,</hi> your <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> are none of mine: ſo that they cannot <hi>deſpiſe and diſobaye mee</hi> that depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you. For your 5.<note place="margin">5. Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts thruſt in by papiſts, which Chriſt never ordained, ſee Sect. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>Sacraments</hi> added vnto my Baptiſme and holie Supper I never ordained as neceſſarie to Salvation, or ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant ſymboles of my death &amp; Paſſion. Your infernall Sacrifice of the <hi>Maſse,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">He. 10.10. &amp;c.</note> as not onlie an jdle and odious repeticion of my pretious death: But a moſt jmpious and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous derogation from the All-ſufficient and eternall merite thereof, I hate and abhorr as an <hi>Antichriſtian Idoll.</hi> They haue doon well that haue with-drawen themſelues from it, and entred into the Congregations of my faithfull Proteſtants; deſpizing and refrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your tedious Multiplicitie of <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> &amp; altogether ridiculouſlie both <hi>Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> and <hi>Profane obſeruances:</hi> for herein they haue honoured and obayed me. Laſtlie then; let other Romanized Engliſh bee
<hi>diſcomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</hi> let their courage faile: and the <hi>number de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe</hi> on your part: let the falſe-Catholicke cauſe be <hi>weakened:</hi> and the enemie thereof
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14468:13"/> be <hi>fortified:</hi> they doe well who are a meanes of this; and pleaſe mee beſt of all that come from among you: ſo farr it is that they <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne</hi> and
<hi>aſsault</hi> me.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue them ſelues.</note>YOu flatter your ſelues, notwithstanding all theſe iniuries ſoothing your conſciences, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>NAy: never perſwade them vnto that. For having builded vpon a <hi>falſe</hi> foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, how can you chooſe but inferr a falſe and preſumptuous concluſion? Your foundation was; that they are<note n="*" place="margin">Sect. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>erring Soules,</hi> departing from my Church: joyning with <hi>Heretickes:</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Sect. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>denying, deſpizing,</hi> and <hi>oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning mee:</hi> which they will never graunt you: which I will never yeeld you: yet thereof you would haue them to be perſwaded. And to that end forſooth would rouze vp their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and <hi>ſound</hi> the bottome of their <hi>hearts</hi> to ſearch and ſee their <hi>diſsimulation.</hi> That they are <hi>Romanists</hi> in heart and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble their faith; I cannot approue it: that they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14468:13"/> vnite themſelues vnto the Proteſtants; I will not blame it: that they doe ſo onlie in a colour to ſaue their Lands and goods; I doe not juſtifie it: that they therfore muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded for <hi>deniers, deſpizers,</hi> &amp; <hi>oppugners</hi> of
<hi>me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Popiſh Prieſt t keth vpon him to judge his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of Chriſt. Mat 7.1.</note> and my faith of truth, in converſing with the Proteſtants, and comming to their <hi>Seruice,</hi> and Churches; how ſhould I jnferr it? yet you take vppon you to prooue it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>DOe yee not as <hi>Peter</hi> denie your ſelues to bee of my Company, &amp;c.<note place="margin">By Peters denyall is prooued that Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Not contented with eſchewing the exerciſe of the Catholicke faith, and participation with the faithfull in profeſsion of conſcience, yee make no Scruple to frequent the rites of a falſe beleefe, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>NO ſir: they doe not.<note place="margin">Doubtfull Catholicks may come to Proteſtant Churches to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Papiſts perſeuere in erroneous Contumacie.</note> For yee Recuſant Papiſts are none <hi>of my companie, my fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, my inheritance, my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ooke, the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith, my Children,</hi> and the like: (as you ſtile your ſelues.) To denie your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, your Religion, and falſe Catholicke
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14468:14"/> Church; is not to renounce mee their <hi>God, Redeemer,</hi> and Saviour; and to <hi>denie my holie Name, and Maieſtie.</hi> Therefore let this whole compariſon betwixt
<hi>Peters</hi> deniall of me, and theirs (as yee ſuppoſe;) goe for naught and cancelled. Onlie I would haue you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;<note place="margin">The Pope is onlie the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of Peter.</note> that your holie Father, the preſumed Succeſſor of this Apoſtle, and all his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers haue learned well his Apoſtaſie; but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find the waie to returne, repent, goe out with him, &amp; weepe bitterlie. My bleſſed<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 16.17.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, had hee not ſlipped from mee in the high Prieſts Hall,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat.
26.58.</note> his continuance in the profeſſion of my name had beene true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian conſtancie. But your perſeverance in your erroneous, hereticall, and jdolatrous courſe, can be no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profane contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and wicked deſperation. Happie then are they who
<hi>eſchew</hi> the <hi>exerciſe of</hi> your <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke</hi> faith, and
<hi>participation</hi> in <hi>profeſsion of Conſcience</hi> with ſuch
<hi>miſ-beleeuers</hi> as <hi>yee are:</hi> Happie who frequent the Rites of <hi>my true friends the Proteſtants,</hi> and partake with them in the ſacred profeſſion of their Religion. Be it known vnto you,<note place="margin">Proteſtants onlie are true Catholicks.</note> and to all men, They onlie are accepted of me for true Catholicks,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14468:14"/> and remaine firmelie vnited to the Church my Spouſe: and all the reſt whatſoever they profeſſe commit the Acts of hereſie; Nay, are abſolutelie either miſ-beleevers, or vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers: <hi>Hereticks</hi> of Chriſtendome, or <hi>Panim</hi> Infidels.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>DAre yee then ſaye that Catholicke Recuſants are not my proper flocke? &amp;c.<note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks are not of the Catholike Church.</note>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The Lord Christ.</head>
                  <p>NAy: dare yee ſaie they are? I ſay, they are the heard of Antichriſt,<note place="margin">Recuſant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Foxes &amp; Wolues.</note> the wilie<note n="*" place="margin">Canti 2.15.</note> Foxes, &amp; the wild Bores that deſtroye my vine: yea, the<note n="*" place="margin">Matt 7.15.</note> ravening Wolues that prey vpon the ſoules of men. If your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved Schiſmaticks be not of their <hi>band,</hi> nor <hi>members,</hi> of their
<hi>Church</hi> and brother-hoode, it is the better for them. For no <hi>companie</hi> is, or
<hi>can be mine,</hi> which <hi>imbraceth</hi> their errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and falſe Catholicke
<hi>Faith;</hi> which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth their traiterous, murderous, and vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall courſe of life.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14468:15"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The aſſured ground where-vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Recuſants ſtand.</note>REcuſants to ſtand vppon an aſſured ground none can iustly denie, or with reaſon call their ſaluation in queſtion, who cleaue stedfastlie to their fore-fathers Faith, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Firſt chriſtened Aunceſtors, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>NO can indeed? Ah yee ſpirits of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption: ſtand they vpon the <hi>aſſured ground</hi> of my Apoſtles doctrine in my word?<note place="margin">Popiſh foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſhew of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</note> No: they are weakelie builded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſand of humane traditions. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I, even I, doe <hi>call their ſaluation in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> They
<hi>cleaue</hi> not <hi>ſtedfaſtlie,</hi> but ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, to the ſuperſtitious Novelties of their late <hi>fore-fathers faith,</hi> who haue departed from the rule of my Religion, whereinto their <hi>firſt chriſtened Anceſtors were converted</hi> by mine Apoſtles and their Coadjutors: <hi>And wherein all their godly Predeceſſors both vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly liued, and happilie died,</hi> before the patche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of your Poperie came in. They haue a ſhadow and ſhew of ſome late praecedent ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations: but the ſoundnes of Antiquitie

<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14468:15"/> from the purer times and truly Apoſtolicall, who ſo ever ſifteth their Moderne faith ſhal find they haue not, for all their great cracks and brags.<note place="margin">Tertullian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> de praeſcript. aduerſus haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>See Iude. Verſ. 3.</hi>
                     </note> And ſo <hi>Tertullian</hi> the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpake well in that: <hi>Dominicum &amp; verum, quod pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us traditum: extraneum &amp; falſum, quod poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius immiſsum.</hi> The truth of the Lord was firſt deliuered to the Saints: but forraine falſhood crept in afterwards.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>THeſe are they which nouriſh the ſparkes of that fire which I came downe to kindle on earth, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Recuſants highly to be comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for their zeale.</note>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THey</hi> are <hi>not</hi> praiſe-<hi>worthie</hi> that praiſe themſelues,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.18.</note> but they whome I the Lord doe praiſe. Now, I doe not allow your proude vaunting of your ſelues: I know your workes, and your waies, that they are full of wickednes and hypocriſie. Are you the men that <hi>nouriſh</hi> the <hi>fire</hi> which I came
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14468:16"/> downe to cauſe to burne <hi>on Earth?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc.
12.49.</note> No: no: <hi>yee know not of what ſpirit you are.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc.
9.55.</note> For with the furious fire of a blind zeale which burneth in your breaſts, haue ye not inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; kindled a ſubterraneal &amp; ſulphureous fire to quench the light of
<hi>Iſraell</hi> in this Realme? and all the goodlie ſhining lampes thereof, to the everlaſting memorie of your perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all all ſhame? Then, at that time, did you ſhew how you doe <hi>maintaine and vphold</hi> that my Law:<note place="margin">Exod. 20.13.</note> 
                     <hi>(Thou ſhalt doe no murder.)</hi> How ſo ever you preſume of the reſt: when you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended &amp; attempted the moſt barbarous,<note place="margin">The Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranicall, vnheard-of, and <hi>Satanicall</hi> deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of King, Queene, Prince, and all the States, the beautie and honour of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in an hower. Oh yee ſonnes of <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> and of
<hi>Balack:</hi> yee baſtard generation, and yee monſters of <hi>Moab!</hi> Let my people ſing: <hi>Faux</hi> of <hi>Moab</hi> is deſtroyed and brought to ſilence in a night.
<hi>Piercie, Catesbie,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Moab</hi> are deſtroyed,<note place="margin">Ier.
48.10.</note> and brought to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in an jnſtant. And <hi>curſed ſhall</hi> hee bee
<hi>that</hi> doth <hi>the worke</hi> of the <hi>Lord negligentlie,</hi> or vnfaithfullie; and with-holdeth his ſword from the bloud of all the brood of <hi>Moab;</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14468:16"/> when her time and judgement ſhall be come. For, doe you glorifie my name that glorie in ſuch workes? being ſorie for nothing more,<note place="margin">Papiſts ſorie that the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon tooke no better effect. Luk. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2. Ioh. 2.25.</note> then that it hath not taken your wiſhed and prayed for effect? Diſſemble it no longer, for <hi>I know you hearts.</hi> Therefore ſhall you be diſhonoured for ever: and the jndeleble blot of your noted infamie ſhall never be put out: you ſhall be known for a ſpotted and peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent generation ſo long as the world endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. Goe to now <hi>yee ſtars in the night: yee greene Bayes in the winter: yee freſh fountaines in the Deſerts:</hi> No: no: yee know your ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles in mine Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Iude ve.
12.13</note> &amp; in the Goſpell well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. <hi>Cloudes without water, carried about with euery wind,</hi> &amp; whiff of vaine jmaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <hi>Wells and pits dryed</hi> in the deſerts: <hi>barraine fig-trees,</hi> if yee be greene in the midſt of Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; when the Winter cometh, <hi>corrupt trees, twice dead, and plucked vp by the rootes: wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Starres,</hi> fallen out of the jnferior hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: <hi>for whome</hi> is <hi>reſerued the blacknes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for euer.</hi> For, to be ſhort; ye walke in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and know not whither yee goe: flatter not your ſelues: your own ſectaries doe not beleeue, much leſſe do they <hi>confeſse</hi> that ye do
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14468:17"/> well: and your vowed enemies, my true and faithfull ſervants and friends, the Engliſh Proteſtants, long agoe haue learned of me to repute and range you in the rancke of thoſe who ſtand aſſuredlie in the ſtate of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks haue no part with Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are of the ſame Church.</note>WIth theſe you may wiſh to conſort in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. To partake in profeſsion of faith. Yee may in bare tearmes auouch as much, but ſhall neuer with reaſon be able to make it good, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>IF they haue no part with you how happie are they? If they <hi>conſort</hi> in conſcience, and <hi>partake</hi> in <hi>profeſsion</hi> of a falſe beleefe with you, they haue no part in me, no part in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but they moſt juſtly and aboundantlie deſerue vnto themſelues the vengeance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall fire.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ome out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Recuſants yee ſtaggering Papiſts.</note> If they will come from among you wholie both in converſation, and in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and follow mee faithfullie with my true profeſſors, ſerving me, <hi>nor in the oldnes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14468:17"/> of the Letter</hi> with a ſervile feare,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.6.</note>
                     <hi>but in the newnes of the Spirit</hi> out of thankefulnes in <hi>loue, from a pure heart, a good conſcience,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1 5.</note> 
                     <hi>and Faith vnfained;</hi> comming out from the <hi>Babel</hi> of your <hi>Superſtitions, Atheiſines,</hi> and
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſies:</hi> let them never care for your defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and infected <hi>merites.</hi> For the kingdome of Heaven belongeth vnto mee by a double right, <hi>Enheritance, and Purchaſe:</hi> In the <hi>one,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bernard</note> I was borne vnto it; in the
<hi>other,</hi> I haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlie deſerved it <hi>through obedience and ſprinckling of my</hi> precious and meritorious <hi>bloud:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.2.</note> and I will giue it them if they can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it by a true and liuelie faith,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.4. &amp;c Ephe. 2.8.9. 2. Cor. 7.1.</note> without regard of any other merite: provided alwaies if they doe their beſt without hypocriſie, to walke before mee in <hi>righteouſnes and true holines</hi> all the daies of their life.<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4. Luk. 1.75.</note> But ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Runnagates, becauſe ye are become perverſe Recuſants, and the ſhameles Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of my Church of <hi>England:</hi> returne, I adviſe you, returne into my fold: els I muſt ſaie vnto you as I ſpake vnto the
<hi>Phariſees</hi> of old: <hi>how can yee eſcape the damnation of Hell.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14468:18"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks are not Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks.</note>ANd are you indeed, aske the Recuſant, and he reiecteth you; aske the Perſecutor, and hee imbraceth you not; Aske the Saints and Angels, and they abhorr you; I neuer yet tooke you for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of mine, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> The Lord Christ.</head>
                  <p>YOur meaning is: your miſcalled <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> are not <hi>Romane</hi> Catholicks. What if that be granted? are they aught the worſe? But let me heare the proofe. <hi>Aske</hi> the
<hi>Recuſants; aske</hi> the <hi>perſecutors,</hi> you meane the Proteſtants, <hi>aske the Saints and Angels:</hi> and you adde of me: <hi>(I neuer yet tooke them for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of mine).</hi> What opinion Recuſants carrie of them neither doe they greatlie, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I that they ſhould at all, regard. The Proteſtants finding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their <hi>pauilions,</hi> yet not acquainted with their ſecret purpoſes, haue no reaſon but in charitie to hope the beſt; that in time they will become good Chriſtians: Yet in wiſedome to ſuſpect, that, being as it were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, neither fiſh nor fleſh,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14468:18"/> Romane Catholicks in opinion, in outward Acts of converſation Statiſts; they will prooue no better in the end then <hi>Obnoxious,</hi> that I may not ſay,
<hi>pernicious,</hi> vnto the ſtate. What talke you fondlie of my <hi>Saints</hi> and
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels?</hi> as though you knew what the ſpirits and ſoules of juſt and perfect men in heaven, and thoſe <hi>Caeleſtiall</hi> and <hi>Sempiternall</hi> Thrones,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1 21.</note> Dominions, Principalities, and Powers doe judge. If they abhorr them, it is becauſe they are falſe-hearted Catholicks like your ſelues, not becauſe they conforme themſelues vnto my Proteſtants. As for me: I will anſwere you as I did ſometime the Phariſes:<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.15.</note> 
                     <hi>(yee iudge after the fleſh: I iudge no man: and if I iudge,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">16.</note> 
                     <hi>this my iudgement is true).</hi> This I ſay then: yee reconciled Romaniſts, ye haue caſt away my <hi>Cognizance,</hi> ye are not of my <hi>familie,</hi> yee are my <hi>foes,</hi> yee are the <hi>Church Malignant,</hi> yee are little better then <hi>Infidels,</hi> your <hi>flocke,</hi> your <hi>fold</hi> is <hi>another,</hi> and not <hi>mine;</hi> your <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures,</hi> your <hi>ſheepheards</hi> are none of
<hi>mine:</hi> and if I returne your owne woords vppon your ſelues, which you preſſe vppon your poore Schiſmaticall ſoules, I am able to make it good. <hi>(Haue no confidence in vaine lying words,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14468:19"/> ſay not in your harts we be catholicks: ye are none: ye are become like black a Moores brats, &amp; like E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian elues.)</hi> Sentence your ſelues ye naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: For I muſt tell you plaine: the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants doe weare my badge and liverie, they are of my <hi>familie, the true Church</hi> and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>of the faithfull:</hi> how dare you call them <hi>perſecutors,</hi> who haue been ſo grieuouſlie and tyrannouſly perſecuted by your Church; As that, in thoſe bloudie times of Queene <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>See,</hi> Foxij Act. &amp; Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> within the ſpace of 4. or 5. yeares about 400. <hi>Martyres,</hi> even for that monſtrous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of
<hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> haue felt the furie of your fire, and ſword? And I muſt laie it to your charge. On the other ſide; they never haue done you any harme, but onlie haue ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigated by neceſſary juſtice, &amp; the ſame tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered with exceeding great mildnes and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, the audacious and horrible Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Rebellions of your popiſh Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: of whome not one, all the daies and Raigne of the late Queene, or of the preſent King, for his conſcience and Religion onlie, hath been put to endure any Capital puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But contrary: yours haue moſt tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; carefully byn dealt withall; by writing,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14468:19"/> by preaching, by other good meanes and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage recalled, if not reclaymed, as wandring and ſtraying ſheepe, into my <hi>pastures, flocke,</hi> and <hi>fold;</hi> and vnto my
<hi>ſheepheards</hi> among the Proteſtants. Surely they are <hi>the Church</hi> which I haue purchaſed with my own bloud: They are <hi>my beautifull</hi> and beloued <hi>Spouſe:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 14.4.</note> They are the Virgins vndefiled with jdola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: white and glorious are their garments; becauſe they are the Robes of myne own jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency: and they are the
<hi>Iſraell</hi> of God which I haue deliuered from your <hi>Aegyptian</hi> bondage. Then, thoſe that joyne in heart with them are true Catholicks, though not Romane Catholicks. Happy are they that are ſyncerely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from among you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. And for the reſt who onely make a ſhew of ſeparation from you <hi>for feare of the world,</hi> hauing euill in their jmaginations; when <hi>the ſecrets</hi> of all hearts ſhall be diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>I the Lord will iudge</hi> both them and you,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note> at the laſt day. In the meane time ſpeake no more, I charge you, of the ſuppoſed punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and calamities of the Engliſh Church: and the yoke whervnder your obſtinate and wilfull <hi>Catholicks</hi> are ſayd to <hi>groane;</hi> neither
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14468:20"/> ſlaunder my Church of <hi>England</hi> any more with cruelty; leaſt I jncreaſe my juſtice vpon you, and reward you double according to your deſerts.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks ſhall receaue Iudgement with Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</note>OVt of my ſight; whome to behold is my griefe, the view of your deformitie I cannot abide. As I did to
<hi>Chore</hi> and his company, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And as in the day of Vengeance I will plague Hereticks and Infidels, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>WHat doe you rayling vpon my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in my name? yet the time is not come that I will ſay to them, or you, or any:<note place="margin">Mat. 7.23.</note> 
                     <hi>(out of my ſight:)</hi> the day of doome and Iudgement is the day of: <hi>Depart from me ye workers of Iniquity.</hi> In the meane time I jnvite in mercy all that will come vnto me; while they are lyving here they may repent, and come:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Now is the accepted time, now is the day of Saluation:</hi> he that now refuſeth it in this world, ſhall never find it in the next. Yet
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14468:20"/> a little while,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.13.</note> and <hi>there</hi> ſhalbe <hi>Iudgement mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciles to them that deſpize mercie.</hi> But the day and time of this mortality muſt firſt be paſt before I ſhut vp all compaſſion from them: for I may call offenders,<note place="margin">Matt. 20.6.</note> and giue them grace to come to me, <hi>at whatſoeuer hower I will.</hi> True:<note place="margin">Abac. 1.13.</note> 
                     <hi>I am a God of pure eyes and cannot behold iniquitie.</hi> In which regard let no man truſt to much vpon my mercy: and let theſe take heed how they joyne praeſumption to infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and grieue my <hi>holy ſpirit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.30.</note> 
                     <hi>wherby I ſeale vp all my choſen vnto the day of rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption.</hi> And ſo I counſaile you, and all men. Yea, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you withall eſpecially, that as I did to <hi>Chorah and his confederates,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Num.
16.32.</note> 
                     <hi>and all that remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within the compaſse of their tabernacle;</hi> as I haue done not only <hi>to Samaria and her Idols,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezech. 16.</note> but to
<hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and her abhominations.<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.16.</note> As I will plague not only the known <hi>Hereticke and Infidell,</hi> but the ſecret Hypocrite and diſſembler alſo, <hi>who for feare or friendſhippe</hi> of any man, departeth from me, and mine, with the like <hi>ſcourges of Scorpions</hi> as the reſt, and the vengeance of eternall fire: ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye alſo come out from the <hi>Sodome, Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and <hi>Babylon</hi> of your <hi>Adulterous</hi> Romiſh
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14468:21"/> 
                     <hi>Synagogue;</hi> becauſe you loue to be partners with her in her vnrighteouſnes; you ſhall ere long aſſuredly be partakers with her of her Plagues: for her judgement is not farr off. In the meane time, from henceforth I commaund you, call not the blynd any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger out of the right way wherin they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to walke: challenge not your poore vnſetled Catholicks any more, thus jdly and ridiculouſly as ye do, <hi>of Apostaſie from my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſeruice, of impugnation of my Faith, of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearing to faction, of yealding to furie, of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking in iniquitie, of exhibiting reuerence to an vngodly ſect, and performing perſonall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance to an Adulterous Synagogue,</hi> for ioyning with my friends the Proteſtants of
<hi>England:</hi> for, as all theſe your ſlanderous raylings, and odious blaſphemies, I vtterly abhorr: ſo be ye certified, that theſe are with me in farr bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſtimation and accompt: yea, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ye backe-byte and bable to the contrary: I ſay; they, they the Proteſtants, are my on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faithfull ſeruants, and the lot of mine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; and I am the lot of theirs.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14468:21"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>NO man can ſerue two Maiſters,<note place="margin">Indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie.</note> &amp;c. You ſay you loue my Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, but you enter into <hi>Bethel</hi> and
<hi>Galgala,</hi> &amp;c. Haue acceſse to my Priests, frequent my Sacraments, clenſe your ſelues, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> The Lord Christ.</head>
                  <p>YOur Generall is true:<note place="margin">Mat. 6.24.</note> 
                     <hi>No man can ſerue two</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary <hi>Maſters;</hi> No ſubiect <hi>two ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie Princes:</hi> but your applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt vnjuſt &amp; vngodly. For, how can this be iuſt which I will neuer juſtifie? nay, which I muſt condemne for the greateſt, and moſt intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable blaſphemy that can be vttered: not onely that you compare my ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants to <hi>Idolaters &amp; Deuils,</hi> and their moſt holy and Chriſtian ſeruices to <hi>Idolatrous and Heathniſh ſacrifices:</hi> but my ſelfe alſo their God and Sauiour, to the <hi>Idolls of Bethel, and Gilgal;</hi> and the mountaine of <hi>Samaria;</hi> to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboams Calues;</hi> to
<hi>Malcham,</hi> and <hi>Baal:</hi> nay, to <hi>Beelzebub</hi> himſelfe. Oh deſperate and helliſh blaſphemy: what are ye now jnferiour (<hi>yee Serpents, yee Vipers,</hi> ye wicked Generation;<note place="margin">Mat. 23.33.</note>) vnto thoſe Caſt-awaies of mine own Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who <hi>ſo reuiled me in the daies of my fleſh while I
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14468:22"/> liued with them?</hi> nay, how are ye not ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our vnto them in wickednes &amp; moſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable praeſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? for they ſpake of me in the time of my humility, when I appeared vnto them onely as a man: but ye in this my day of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> now I am ſitting at the right hand of my Fathers Maieſty;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.21.</note> 
                     <hi>farr aboue all principalities and powers, and euery name that is named in this world and in the next.</hi> Therefore ye are curſed with a curſe: and looke ye well vnto it, that this be not the vnpardonable ſinne, <hi>&amp; Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy againſt the holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Marc. 3.29. Luc. 12.10. Heb. 6.4. &amp;c.</note> ſo that it be
<hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible</hi> for you <hi>to be renewed vnto Repentance.</hi> As for thoſe your Catholicks at whome ye rayle vnder the names of <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, of
<hi>Samaritans,</hi> of libertine <hi>Corinthians,</hi> of <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> of ſwearers by God and <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham,</hi> and of wicked <hi>Ahab;</hi> if they loue <hi>my Temple,</hi> (that is none of yours); becauſe they are comming on vnto it, and haue ioyned with my ſeruants in profeſſion, then are they no diſſemblers: But if they are ſtill enamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>your Temple,</hi> (which ye ſay <hi>is mine</hi> but falſely;) by my ſelfe (but not by your Embaſſage, ye ſhall not ſpeake for me:) I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uize them better minds. Yf they be my ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uants
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14468:22"/> and my Children; let them loue me with all their hearts ſyncerely; not in words and colour onely: but in workes &amp; truth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; and ſerue me, as they doe, among the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in the faith of truth. That they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe; if they haue acceſſe to <hi>your Prieſts;</hi> frequent <hi>your Sacraments;</hi> haue in reuerence <hi>your rites and Ceremonies,</hi> honour <hi>your ſeruice;</hi> proſtrate themſelues before <hi>your defiled Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, adore at the houre of your</hi> direfull <hi>ſacrifice:</hi> All which you call
<hi>mine,</hi> but I diſclame them all; as I doe alſo your <hi>Confeſsion and penance.</hi> For will you neuer learne,<note place="margin">Popiſh prieſts none of Chriſts ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> that your <hi>characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſacrifizing Prieſts</hi> neuer ſpra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g from my diuine ordinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? neither can be numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong any of thoſe whom I,<note place="margin">Ephe.
4.8.</note> when <hi>I aſcended vp to Heauen and led captiuitie Captiue, gaue as gifts to men:</hi> ſome <hi>Apoſtles, ſome &amp;c. for the perfecting of the Saints for the worke of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, &amp;c.</hi> Two Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts I haue ordained in my Church to confirme and ſeale vp the faith of my Choſen which they haue in me. <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and my <hi>Holy Supper:</hi> as few as may be; &amp; moſt ſignifica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of my death &amp; paſſion, &amp; price of my rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption. The other 5. <hi>(Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> &amp; <hi>Penance, Matrimonie, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14468:23"/> Vnction,</hi> and <hi>holy Ordination</hi>) Let the moſt of them be ſacred actions: but as ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall ſignes, and ſeales of this great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of my Rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption; that is, properly as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,</hi> I neuer did appoint the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They are added ſo of humane,<note place="margin">1. Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> &amp; of your own jnue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and jnſtitution.
<hi>Confirmation</hi> after Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, as it was in vſe in the Primitiue Church, and in the Apoſtolical times, is good &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.<note place="margin">2. Confeſſion and Penance.</note> 
                     <hi>Confeſsion and penance</hi> are by you abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as a ſnare to entangle the reputation, and to ſlay the ſoules of my people. For yee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the ſame as a neceſſary Sacrament; ye call for a particular enumeratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes, if it be poſſible; the Act, with all the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof:<note place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incent. Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no tract. de Paenit.</note> when, where, in what manner, and how often it hath been committed: not only wicked &amp; vngodly, but euen fooliſh, j<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and vnfruitfull words: yea the very ſecret <hi>thoughts</hi> and intents of the hart muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred and <hi>layd open to the Priest.</hi> And ye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt a moſt ridiculous <hi>Penance</hi> as a <hi>ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> for ſinne;<note place="margin">3. Matrimony Heb. 13.4. Ephe. 5.32.</note> for which no man can ſatisfie but my ſelfe alone.
<hi>Mariage is honourable in all:</hi> and it <hi>ſignifieth</hi> the myſticall <hi>vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwixt me and my Church:</hi> yea, &amp; to be ſolemnized in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14468:23"/> open view of a congregation it is an ancient and moſt wholſome Cuſtome,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen. 29.21. Iudic. 14.10.</hi> Tertull. lib. de pudicitia pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes noc occul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae coniunctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp;c. Conc. Carth. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> &amp; Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Conſtitution; for the avoyding of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giaries, of Clandeſtine adulteries, fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, jnceſts, and ſuch like jmpieties. But I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer required it to be held for a Sacrament of the Church; it being alſo lawfull and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable among the very Infidels, who are not within the Church.<note place="margin">4. Extreme Vnction.</note> 
                     <hi>Vnction</hi> of the ſicke with oyle was a Ceremonie both<note n="*" place="margin">Marc. 6.13.</note> in, and immediatly after the daies of my habitation here on Earth, which I allowed to <hi>mine Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles &amp; Primitiue Elders of the Church,</hi> becauſe by the meanes of that and prayer I was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to giue vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a gift of healing for the recouery of the ſicke &amp; weake.<note place="margin">Iam. 5.14.</note> But now ſince the gift hath been withdrawn, with many <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of like qualitie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Marc. 16.17.18.</note> granted for <hi>tokens &amp; eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of beleeuers</hi> on me in thoſe dayes: therfore it ſhall be but humane idlenes, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, &amp; preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, to continue the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny without a grace. Much more is it audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, if not extreme, impiety to deuize a new Ceremony, &amp; a new name of <hi>Extreme Vnctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> and therunto to forge a grace. As for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſmeering or anoyling vſed in your Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14468:24"/> at Baptiſme, or other where, I diſclame,<note place="margin">5. Orders.</note> and renounce it, as the ſcumme, and filth of your owne braines.
<hi>Ordination</hi> of biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, as it is in vſe amongſt my Engliſh Proteſtants, <hi>is both ancient and Authentick;</hi> beeing, euen from the <hi>prime and purer</hi> Churches,<note place="margin">Socr. li. 1. c. 11 Sozom. lib 1. cap. 22.</note> reputed
<hi>Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call:</hi> but by you it is Mudded and polluted with a ſacrifizing Prieſt-hood; to the moſt ſhamefull, and ſlaunderous derogation, and impeachment of That mine euerlaſting Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,<note place="margin">Popiſh Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies apiſh &amp; ridiculous.</note> and Office after the order of <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech. Your multiplicity,</hi> and abſurdity <hi>of</hi> moſt apiſh, and toyiſh <hi>Ceremonies:</hi> as ducking, croſſing, cloſing, &amp; opening of hands, <hi>Hoſt-eleuating,</hi> loud-bawling, ſecret Mumbling, and the like: are fitter for a Theater, then for the Church. What reuerence can yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to ſuch jrreuerend, childiſh, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Adminiſtrations? To be ſhort: your diſhonorable <hi>ſeruice;</hi> your deteſtable <hi>Altar;</hi> your hypocriricall creeping, and caſting downe your bodyes; your no leſſe odious lifting vp jmpure harts and hands; your i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous adoratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; your contumacious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour of blynd zeale; your <hi>dreadfull,</hi> nay
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14468:24"/> direfull, &amp; abhominable, <hi>ſacrifice;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the popiſh Maſſe.</note> &amp; therfore abhominable becauſe an offring not only of my paſſion, but of my body; a ſpirituall, &amp; a Carnall; a bloudy, and vnbloudy Sacrifice; indeed, a Sacrifice, and no Sacrifice: becauſe not only a memory of me the Redeemer of my Choſen is ſolemnly celebrated, and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſented; but a propitiation alſo for the liuing and the dead is pretended to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; directly croſſing, and contrary to that one
<hi>Oblation</hi> of my ſelfe once offred, not without bloud:<note place="margin">Heb.
10.14.</note> 
                     <hi>whereby for euer I haue conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated and perfected them that are ſanctified:</hi> wherein by the <hi>Eternall ſpirit I offered vp my ſelfe vnto God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 9.12.13.14.</note> 
                     <hi>and found eternall redemption for them.</hi> All theſe are not the workes of my Children, and ſeruants; and therfore I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you once againe, vnder the penalty of my great and Eternall curſe, that yee ceaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further to lead the blynd out of the way, whome you haue peruerted too farr already, and will not ſuffer them ſo much as to enter a deliberation to returne vnto the flocks of my Sheapheards againe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:14468:25"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks juſtly repelled from the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note>HEre you ſtraine courteſie, here fleſh and bloud reclaimeth the ſpirit taking the foyle, and the old man triumphing. Some of you diſcharge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of their crimes by my Stewards ouer rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous auſterity, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>How dare you proffer to approach to my Altar, where ſo great a Maieſtie is reſident? &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>IS not this an ouer-Rigorous auſterity and moſt apparent in you? Firſt, to inhibite them the Churches of the Proteſtants; and after to exclude them from your own myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries &amp; Oratories alſo. You ſay nay. For firſt, you would haue them to <hi>Confeſse</hi> themſelues guilty for ioyning with the Proteſtants, and to purpoſe amendment of that fault, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue <hi>your abſolution,</hi> and to doe <hi>penaunce,</hi> and ſo to be purged, and ſo be prooued worthy to come vnto <hi>your Altar.</hi> But I ſay vnto you ſtill, <hi>your Altar</hi> is <hi>not my Altar,</hi> my <hi>great Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie</hi> is not there reſident, but onely the pettie Maieſtie of your profane bread, neither is your <hi>penaunce,</hi> your
<hi>pardon,</hi> your <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> my ordination. Therefore they who refuſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14468:25"/> theſe things from you are guiltles before me: and (as yee ſaye) <hi>in this one thing happie,</hi> that they are ſuſpended and reiected of you. And I denounce a woe againſt you that <hi>Cal good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and euill good; ſweet ſower, &amp; ſower ſweet;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſay. 5.20.</note> 
                     <hi>put light for darknes, and darknes for light.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>WEll then,<note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks are to be praeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for Haereticks, and why.</note> among my Catholicks ſince you are not, where ſhall I find you? where, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Caluiniſt taketh you for Proſelytes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The poore Catholick ſcandalized at your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>WHat? and will you ſtill make me the Patrone of your lyes? ſurely, I doe not hold them among my true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, no more then I doe your ſelues: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet doe I conclude;<note place="margin">The Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not diſſembling Catholicks.</note> that cleauing to the Proteſtants they <hi>cleaue to ſectaries:</hi> neither doe <hi>I pronounce</hi> them
<hi>Proteſtants:</hi> neither do I allow their reproofe, either <hi>in priuate talke,</hi> or in priuate opinion, of the Proteſtant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings: neither are thoſe proceedings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from the faith: nor yet their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14468:26"/> 
                     <hi>houſes of Idolatry,</hi> as ye blaſpheme: So that albeit <hi>by</hi> their <hi>preſence</hi> with them, in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance they <hi>honour,</hi> by <hi>obaying</hi> they
<hi>allow,</hi> by <hi>example</hi> they <hi>further,</hi> by <hi>deeds</hi> they
<hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme,</hi> by <hi>diſsembling</hi> they <hi>establiſh</hi> thoſe procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings: albe-it they goe to thoſe houſes <hi>as one of them;</hi> they ſit there <hi>as one of them,</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue themſelues reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly <hi>as one of them;</hi> yet in all this, or in any of theſe they cannot be defined eyther <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> or <hi>Haereticks.</hi> In a word, howſoeuer they are reputed <hi>Proſelyts</hi> of the <hi>Caluiniſt</hi> (as you terme the true <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>): and howſoeuer your <hi>poore Catholicks,</hi> poore indeed and voyde of true Catholicke faith,<note place="margin">Diſſembling Catholicks no Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</note> are <hi>ſcandalized</hi> of them; though they may be <hi>loſt ſheepe</hi> (for the time) and
<hi>diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers,</hi> yet are they no <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> being not diuided from the true Church; much leſſe <hi>at the brinck of bottomles haereſie</hi> in that reſpect.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thoſe which goe to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles of Haereticall rites are iuſtly and properly called ſ hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks.</note>ABhominable is Schiſme, and horrible is the name of Schiſmaticke, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When my Church in her firſt prime, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:14468:26"/>
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> The Lord Christ.</head>
                  <p>Schiſme is a ſeparation from the faith of truth; and the true Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of Saints.<note place="margin">What is Schiſme.</note> And therefore all thoſe Chriſtians vpon whatſoeuer intent &amp; purpoſe of heart, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Feare of the Aduerſity and Croſſes, or for loue of the proſperity, eaſe, and ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of this preſent euill world, who do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort themſelues (though but for a time) with the Iewiſh, Turkiſh, or any other Heathniſh profeſſion, let them be cenſured for ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Reuolters, till they returne into the Church againe. But herevpon how can you charge your cunning Catholicks of ſchiſme, for aſſociating in their actions with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants? Firſt you are to proue the one to be
<hi>Haereticks,</hi> their Aſſemblies alſo, and <hi>rites hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall;</hi> which you can neuer do: and then forewarne the other vnder the penalty of Schiſmaticall reproch to adhaere vnto them. Be it that ſome of them, (for all, I know, who know the hearts, doe not) repute and take the Proteſtants for Haereticks; for that is the poynt you preſſ vppon them; and yet like
<hi>Ambidexters,</hi> Machiauels, and Temporizers,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14468:27"/> only for feare, or for loue of the earth and earthly things, againſt their conſciences, will make a ſhew to be on their ſide: yet I ſay, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhal their own falſe opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yours, conclude them to be Schiſmaticks in joyning with my Church: howſoeuer they may be convicted of themſelues for notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hypocrites and diſſemblers; and ſo be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable in my ſight. For I cannot like it that they, or you, or any ſhould diſſemble with me,<note place="margin">Ioſue 9.9.</note> or my people. The <hi>Gibeonites</hi> in that they ſought the friendſhip of my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Ioſua</hi> and his hoſt, did not offend me; in that they ſought it by diſſimulation, they did not pleaſe me:<note place="margin">verſ. 21.</note> Therfore for the one, I ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their liues; and for the other, I adjudged them to perpetuall ſeruitude. The remnant of thoſe Iewes who dwell now among the Nations, who are baptized, and profeſſe Chriſtianity, therein are no offenders; but being true, as it is reported of many of them, that they ſtill are judaicall in opinion, and that the vayle of <hi>Moyſes</hi> is layd ouer their hearts; in that I diſclame and deteſt them as forlorne miſ-beleeuers, and my ſworne Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. So, let euery one of yours, either be as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14468:27"/> they profeſſe, vnfayned Chriſtians;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Perfect ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks.</hi> Schiſma facere ab vnitate Christi, aut in Schiſmate eſse profecto malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est, &amp; magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: nec om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninò fieri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vt Chriſtus det Schiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co non fidem ſed ſacrilegum errorem, aut in Chriſto radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus fixerit, aut Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico Chriſtus ſit origo &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put. Aug. lib. <hi>4.</hi> contra Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Gramm.</note> or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe as they are, falſe-hearted and falſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onated Catholicks: Schiſmaticks they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be that profeſſe the truth in the Church; They only are ſuch who being runnagates and hereticks maintaine falſhoods, with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall ſeparation from the Church. Neither yet doe I allow them for good and faithfull Chriſtians, who would be ſo reputed, and are not: for they only are ſuch whoſe opinion and profeſſion agree togither in the truth; that is, who profeſſe the truth in ſyncerity.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Know,<note place="margin">Proteſtants cannot be of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke church, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their faith can be ſalvation.</note> I know what it is that lyeth at your heart, &amp;c. Yee are not perſwaded forſooth that the Protestants Religion is ſo abhominable, &amp;c. To take your ſelues for a particular Church, is vnpoſsible for a headleſse multitude, who haue neither Temple, Altar, Priest, nor Sacrifice, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtinct members, nor anyband of Vnion, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well you may thinke of going at the latter day ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Heauen nor to Hell, as to thinke in this life a Newtrality, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Will you diuide my Church, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:14468:28"/>To ſay that Protestants may by their profeſsion be ſaued, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> The Lord Christ.</head>
                  <p>OH ye wretched and wicked Prieſts of Antichriſt; I know well, I know, that <hi>my Church, my Spouſe, my body myſticall, my chast Turtle, my Citie, my Kingdome, my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.19. Mat. 18.7.</note> the <hi>piller of Truth,</hi> is but one. For albeit in my viſible Church <hi>there muſt bee Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.20. Mat. 13 24. &amp;c. Mat. 3.12.</note> 
                     <hi>and Scandals,</hi> for the triall of my choſen: for that in <hi>my houſe</hi> there are <hi>veſſels of honour &amp; diſhonour:</hi> in <hi>my field</hi> there is <hi>Corne &amp; Tares:</hi> in <hi>my garner</hi> there is <hi>Wheat &amp; Chaff:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 13.47. Gen. 7.8.</note> in <hi>my Net</hi> there is <hi>good and bad Fiſh:</hi> in <hi>my Arke</hi> there are <hi>cleane and vncleane beaſts:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 3.2. Rom. 6.17.</note> and there will be alwaies ſome of whome it may be ſayd; <hi>Beware of Dogs.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 7.15. Act. 20.29.</note> 
                     <hi>Marke them that make diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions among you, and auoyde them. Beware of falſe Prophets. Grieuous Wolues ſhall enter in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you.</hi> Yet as vnto my choſen there is but <hi>one way,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh.
14.1.</note> 
                     <hi>One truth, one life:</hi> ſo <hi>they are all baptized by one ſpirit into one body.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.13. Epheſi. 4.4. &amp;c.</note> For <hi>there is one bodie and one ſpirit, euen as they are called in one hope of their vocation; one Lord, one faith, one Baptizme, one God and father of all, which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14468:28"/> is aboue all, and through all, and in them all: One ſheepheard and one fold. My Doue is alone,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 10. Cantic. 6.</note> The company of my choſen is but one Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints, partly triumphant in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and partly militant on Earth: But muſt ye therefore be that one? Do ye take it for graunted that I will not yeeld you? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but begging of the Queſtion? How dare ye ſay in my name that they are <hi>blind and impious who imagine holines in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants prayers, or ſaluation to bee found in their Faith?</hi> For I, euen I, pronounce vnto you: their prayers are holie;<note place="margin">A true ſauing faith.</note> and their faith is a ſauing faith; which aſcribeth and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth the ſole and whole worke and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, and the purchaſe of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto me alone. And to ſay, that by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other profeſſion a man may be ſaued, is indeed, to make <hi>an other God,</hi> and <hi>Summum bonum, beſides me,</hi> and to make <hi>me none,</hi> or euil, or jnſufficient at the leaſt, which in truth ye prowde Papiſts doe,<note place="margin">Papiſts ioyne their own merits with the Death of Chriſt in the purchaſe of ſaluation.</note> in vaunting the merits of your owne defectiue and jnfected works, as coadjutors to the purchaſe of Eternall glory, with the obedience and ſprinckling of my precious bloud: as though I had not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14468:29"/> made a full and perfect ſatisfaction without your ayde or helpe. But thus ye boldly and preſumptuouſly diminiſh &amp; diſhonour me, and my all-ſufficiently meritorious Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and yet ye malapertlie charge my true beleeuers of that fault whereof your ſelues are guilty. Shall I not punniſh you for this thing?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The perfect oppoſition and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks &amp; Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note>IF on the other ſide, you ioyne Caluiniſts with Catholicks in one Church, then ſet together the Woolfe with the Lambe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For aſmuch as my dreadfull Euchariſt is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragably beleeued by the one to be my true body, &amp;c. Of other maine differences conſider, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>THis generall oppoſition betwixt you Papiſts, and my true profeſſors the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants I doe allow: prouided alwaies that yee are the <hi>Wolues,</hi> the <hi>Lyons,</hi> the
<hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hawkes;</hi> and they the <hi>Lambes,</hi> the <hi>Harts,</hi> the <hi>Partridges;</hi> and that your <hi>Religion</hi> is the <hi>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mized,</hi> theirs the <hi>ſure;</hi> yours
<hi>vnpoſsible,</hi> theirs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14468:29"/> 
                     <hi>infallible;</hi> yours newly <hi>reared by mans imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, cheriſhed for pollicie, &amp;c:</hi> Theirs <hi>founded</hi> by my ſelfe from the beginning, vppon my ſelfe the <hi>Rocke.</hi> What other Haereticks doe, or how they injuriouſly reuile,
<hi>vpbraide</hi> as <hi>an Idoll, teare, ſpit at,</hi> and <hi>treade vnder foote my dreadfull Euchariſt:</hi> What is that to theſe true Chriſtians, whome opprobriouſly yee call
<hi>Hugonots?</hi> Sure it is, they for their parts moſt conſtantly and deuoutly beleeue my true body, (jmpute no jdle <hi>Manichean</hi> phantaſie vnto them) and the perſonall preſence of my Deity in the <hi>Euchariſt:</hi> (I know their faith;<note place="margin">Popiſh adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of bread.</note>) &amp; me they <hi>adore with due veneration;</hi> though not the Element that repreſenteth my true body: Neither doe they commit ſuch a myſticall and ſpirituall kind of murder and mangling of my body asye do, who profeſſe,<note place="margin">Papiſts feed corporallie, they ſay, vpon Chriſt when they feed on him in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. See Ferus in Iohn cap. 6. The number of Popiſh Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</note> howſoeuer in termes ye diſclame it, not only a ſpiritual, but a corporall feeding thervpon: brutiſh Cannibals as yee are. As touching the other <hi>maine differences</hi> between them and you in the particulars; Know yee; that I neuer ordained the <hi>number</hi> of 7. <hi>Sacraments,</hi> but onely Baptiſme, and my holy Supper: your <hi>vſe of Images</hi> I ſcorne, and abhorr,<note place="margin">Images.</note>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14468:30"/> being directly contrary to the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of my morall Law:
<hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. &amp; monu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Foxe pag <hi>130.</hi>
                     </note> though your Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> commaunded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be taken for Laymens Kalenders:<note place="margin">Inuocation of Saints.</note> your <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Saints</hi> is a derogation from <hi>my glory</hi> which <hi>I will not giue to any other:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſay. 42.8.</note> I neuer commanded you by any praecept; I neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited you by any godly example; I neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged you by any promiſe in my holy word; to any ſuch deuotion. <hi>Your forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſinnes</hi> by your Popes indulgences,<note place="margin">Indulgences.</note> and your ſelling of <hi>pardons</hi> is paltry trifling and prophane Marchandizing in my holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.<note place="margin">Heavenly glorie.</note> What
<hi>heauenly glorie</hi> do you dreame of, that my faithfull Proteſtants beleeue not much better then yee are able;<note place="margin">Popiſh diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall paines.</note> 
                     <hi>your difference of infernall paines</hi> I am not acquainted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: I know none but eternall fire prepared for the diuell and his adhaerents; your tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall <hi>purgatorie flames</hi> are but
<hi>poëticall fables;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Purgatorie a poëtical fable. Iuſtification.</note> 
                     <hi>your Iuſtification</hi> of the liuing by faith and works together, is partly coyned in your owne forge, and partly raked vp out of the Phariſaicall pride.<note place="margin">Praier for the dead.</note> 
                     <hi>Your praying for the dead</hi> is bootles, they hauing now their Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14468:30"/> paſſed on them: as the day of death hath left them, ſo the day of finall Iudgement ſhall finde them, either bleſſed or curſed for euer. No prayers now ſhall preuaile, or hurt them any whit at all.<note place="margin">Popiſh faith, hope, &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</note> Moreouer <hi>your faith</hi> is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Confidence; nay rather an jmplicite and vnknowne aſſent, you know not vnto what; full of diſtruſt and diffidence: <hi>your hope</hi> builded thereuppon muſt needs be hopeles, and voyd of ſound and heauenly comfort:
<hi>your Charitie</hi> to me is very ſlender and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme like theirs once of
<hi>Laodicea:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 3.15.</note> for yee loue your ſelues as well as me; your owne merits you joyne with mine, vngratefully diminiſhing my meritorious ſacrifice and the price of my bloud. Oh ſinfull Nation; ſupply yee my pure and perfect obedience with your owne foule and filthie righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? Is this your loue to me to pretend the purchaſe of heauen together with me? thus to be ouer-enamoured of your ſelues? Fie, Fie; I cannot endure a Co-partner with me in this great worke of Redemption and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Therefore your jmagined
<hi>freewill</hi> to good: your <hi>merits</hi> of congruence, and of worthines, where are they? your <hi>faſtings</hi> and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14468:31"/> 
                     <hi>prayers,</hi> conceited, and practiſed, not onely as means but as
<hi>meritorious</hi> workes of eternall life, <hi>I hate;</hi> and will ſurely puniſh as the fumes and fomes of the pride of your old A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. As for <hi>ſinnc</hi> yee knowe not the power thereof that ſuppoſe any one to be veniall in it ſelfe, being committed againſt ſo eternall and jnfinit a Maieſtie, as I am. And what haue you to doe with my counſell and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of <hi>predeſtination?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Predeſtinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </note> Will you or can you infringe the infallible Certainty therof that ye teach men to doubt of my loue? why doe yee not tell them rather, that though they cannot chooſe but doubt, by reaſon of their many,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.58.</note> and mighty ſinnes, which is humane jnfirmitie; yet they ought to be
<hi>ſtedfaſt and vnmoouable in their faith,</hi> being builded on me,<note place="margin">Mal.
3.6. Pro. 19.21. Heb. 13.5.</note> who <hi>am God; and am not changed;</hi> whoſe <hi>Counſell is immutable;</hi> who <hi>will not faile neither yet forſake</hi> them that put their truſt in me: yea though they beleeue not without great weaknes,<note place="margin">2. Tim 2.13.</note> yet I am God, <hi>faithfull</hi> and true, <hi>and cannot deny myſelfe.</hi> Finally, what meane you to adde vnto my canonicall <hi>ſcriptures</hi> the <hi>Apocryphall</hi> writings of <hi>Iudith, Tobias, Maccabees,</hi> and others: which I neuer yet
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14468:31"/> allowed to be put into the canon. Nay, to thruſt in your owne vnwritten
<hi>Traditions</hi> and <hi>Papall conſtitutions</hi> to make them of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall authoritie with the ſame:<note place="margin">Neſanda ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creta.</note> Theſe your nefarious hidden doctrines I will haue can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled and aboliſhed: I cannot abide that yee ſhould goe a whoring after your owne ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations. Goe and learne what that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: <hi>In vaine they worſhip me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 15.9.</note> 
                     <hi>reaching for doctrines mens precepts.</hi> And that:<note place="margin">verſ. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>Euery plant which mine heauenly Father hath not planted, ſhalbe rooted vp.</hi> Thus haue you, in deed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the whole ſumme of Religion
<hi>toſsed ouer euerie stone, reuerſed the whole frame of faith, and turned all vpſide downe.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take you heed, yee obſtinate Recuſants, leaſt your departure and diuiſion from my true Church be a more then ſufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of your heauy Iudgement with
<hi>Arrius, Neſtorius, Eutyches,</hi> I adde, with <hi>Manichees, Marcionits, Pelagians;</hi> and
<hi>other old Haereticks,</hi> in the <hi>bottomles pit.</hi> for that you haue not <hi>in one point,</hi> but in many, varied from the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:14468:32"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Churches of Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks are.</note>CAluiniſme then being doctrine ſo diabolicall, &amp;c. Oh how illuſion bewitcheth you, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Their profane bread, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Their Rites and Ceremonies, &amp;c. As Faſts &amp; Holy daies, &amp;c. Yea, their Churches and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, &amp;c. Bethel was my houſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> The Lord Christ.</head>
                  <p>SVrely, the <hi>Scriptures, praiers, and Churches</hi> of Haereticks are not well pleaſing vnto me: They are abhominable Papiſme, therefore being the verie doctrine of deuils; your popiſh <hi>Scripture</hi> as being none of my word,<note place="margin">Popiſh Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine vulgar e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition authe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke among the Papiſts, very errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> but <hi>the word</hi> of the deuill, ſo falſe and adulterated, ſo poyſoned, and full of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as it is in your latine vulgar edition au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by your Trent Councell, <hi>oppugning</hi> vndermyning, and overthwarting <hi>my true faith,</hi> and Catholike <hi>Church</hi> I
<hi>diſclame</hi> as a <hi>counterfait coppie,</hi> and <hi>renounce</hi> altogether, as no writ of myne.<note place="margin">Popiſh pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> 
                     <hi>Your praiers</hi> alſo are no better in
<hi>mine eares</hi> then the <hi>howling of Wolues</hi> that prey vppon the ſoules of men; the
<hi>low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Oxen,</hi> and the <hi>roaring of Bulls, ſcreeching of Owles,</hi> and
<hi>Night-Rauens,</hi> yelling and bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14468:32"/> Infernall blaſphemies againſt my ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Maieſtie, in vnknowne and vnconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, in loud bawling, in diſcording from my heart, both tongues and tunes.<note place="margin">Popiſh Prieſts.</note> 
                     <hi>Your prieſts</hi> are perfect <hi>Chemarims,</hi> and
<hi>Prieſts of Baal;</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the very <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> his <hi>heralds,</hi> and proctors, his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Angels of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of darknes.<note place="margin">Popiſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</note> Goe yee and <hi>ſuck</hi> the <hi>adders Eggs, leſſe poyſonable</hi> out of doubt <hi>then your Communion bread</hi> and <hi>cup.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Popiſh Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> Your Ceremonies are <hi>not few,</hi> but <hi>moſt fantaſticall;</hi> offenſiue both in their nomber, and in their nature, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, and plainly ridiculous jmitations part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Heathniſh ſuperſtitions, and partlie of thoſe Rites which my heauenly Father ſometimes ordayned to his people <hi>Iſraell.</hi> Your
<hi>faſtes</hi> are fiſh delicates: wine,<note place="margin">Popiſh faſts.</note> and other dainty fare; farr more jncentiue of filthie Luſt in pampering of the body then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foode: and your abſtinence ſometimes a feaſting, ſometimes a moſt Phariſaicall and
<hi>Hypocriticall</hi> ſowring of your faces, and other oſtentation of <hi>will-worſhip in neglecting the body:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Coloſs. 2.22.23.</note> 
                     <hi>not in any honour to the ſatisfying of the fleſh</hi> (as myne Apoſtle paints it out in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Coloſſians.) Your <hi>holy dayes,</hi> ſo
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14468:33"/> 
                     <hi>your Churches</hi> and <hi>your Temples,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Churches de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Papiſts.</note> are dedicated not onely to the holy Trinitye, and to other true and worthy ſaynts &amp; Martyrs, many of them,<note place="margin">Dunſtan.</note> but ſome to vile &amp; jmpious <hi>Traytors,</hi> and <hi>Coniurers,</hi> and ſuch like abhominable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: beſids to the exerciſe of your Idolatrous and ſuperſtitious deuotious, which I cannot abyde. Therefore they are <hi>not more holy, no more my howſes,</hi> no more the places of my ſanctuary, which you frequent: nay, all your meetings, ſynagogues, and aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies I vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abhorr? what talke yee of <hi>Bethel?</hi> of <hi>Geri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zim?</hi> of <hi>Sichem?</hi> of the Chriſtian Churches? For yee goe up to <hi>Beth-auen;</hi> and ſtand vpon mount
<hi>Eball:</hi> and commit jdolatrie in the hill of <hi>Samaria.</hi> The <hi>Turkiſh Temples</hi> are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian,<note place="margin">The Pope.</note> and ſo are yours. Your
<hi>High Priest</hi> of the Romane ſea is now deemed fitly of my Chriſtian Churches the very Apoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Iudas of the world,<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.5.</note> and the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Apocalypticall Beaſt: ſo is euery one, that receiueth his marke and jmbraceth his doctrine, a Reuolter from my faith of truth. Therefore all your prayers and ſeruice offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto me I haue in Execration.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:14468:33"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>OH think not it can be to my worſhip which is ſo wicked.<note place="margin">The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prayer how vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable.</note> Remember that Altar is raiſed vp againſt Altar &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Againſt my venerable Alter there is erected a plaine communion Table &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And ſtolen away with them her ornaments and to couer the ragges wherewith they are rigd, Iet vp and downe clad in hir robes, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>It is ſo: it muſt be ſo (yee Papiſts:) betweene your <hi>Altar,</hi> your
<hi>Prieſts,</hi> your <hi>Sacraments,</hi> your <hi>ſeruice,</hi> your <hi>faith:</hi> and the Altar, the Preachers, the ſacraments, the ſeruice, the faith of the proteſtants there is, and euer wilbe an oppoſition: neither <hi>poſsibly can be any vnitie, concord, or conformitie.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Papiſts Altar &amp; Idol.</note> For your <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar</hi> of jmagined Sacrifice propitiatory who hath required at your hands? your abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable <hi>host</hi> which I neuer acknowledged to be my bleſſed Body I know and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne for a deteſtable Idol.<note place="margin">The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</note> But their <hi>plaine Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table,</hi> is both neceſſarie, and ſeemely, to ſet my holy and heauenly bread vppon; not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14468:34"/> 
                     <hi>a baſe and vnprofitable</hi> peece of Bread, as yee blaſpheme, but bread honoured, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated by mine owne ordinance, for an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting memoriall of my death and Paſſion: To the end that all beleeuing ſoules which feed thereon with a true and liuely Faith, might be confirmed and nouriſhed vnto E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life. Dare yee call this <hi>an Idoll,</hi> (yee wicked jmpes,) <hi>of a contemptible ſupper?</hi> yee are alſo the
<hi>miniſters of darknes,</hi> yee ſtamped <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> they are myne only true &amp; faithfull Embaſſadours who faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire &amp; intreat my people in my name to be reconciled vnto god. For <hi>theirs</hi> is the <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, worthy, ſound, vndoubted faith</hi> of truth: <hi>yours</hi> (to returne your owne words becauſe they fit you well, as ſwords and arrowes into your owne hartes) <hi>a Baſterd, Counterfait, vncertaine, and fained miſcreance.</hi> But finally what is this your blame in the ſeruice of my Saints, and
<hi>publique praier,</hi> of the Proteſtants? what poſitiue <hi>Corruption</hi> finde you therin that you will haue it <hi>abhominable in my ſight?</hi> Onely you alledge: <hi>(it is a forme of prayer, a ſhadow of diuine ſeruice wholy tending to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of hereſie, not onely &amp;c. but directly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14468:34"/> in defiance of me, &amp; my mysteries, and of the faith Catholicke, which is put into Engliſh to Inſinuate that my Church erreth in not vſing the vulgar)</hi> A forme of prayer it is indeed,<note place="margin">The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants forme of prayer.</note> and an excellent forme; not a ſhadow, but a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall forme of diuine ſeruice; wholy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the maintenance of the pure faith, and the ouerthrowe of the popiſh Hereſies,<note place="margin">Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</note> ſuperſtitions, &amp; jdolatries. In regard where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Ancient and approued Rites, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ceremonies are fitting and ſignificant for edification, it neither diſanulleth, nor ſuppreſſeth: not ſtumbling at euery ſtraw, to be ſcandalized with things indifferent, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer other oppoſites ſay or write to the contrarie: but it retaineth and ordaineth prudently and deuoutly, Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſuch nature and qualitie as theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and diſſolute times do much require.<note place="margin">Veſtiments and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> As touching the <hi>ornaments</hi> or
<hi>veſtments</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>their</hi> Church yee ſpeake vnlearnedly and
<hi>ſpitefully</hi> to ſaye they were <hi>stollen</hi> from your Church; and the proteſtants
<hi>Iet vp and downe in your Robes.</hi> They know, the ſtollen attire of the <hi>Strumpet</hi> of Babylon will ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the <hi>virgin,</hi> the daughter of God.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14468:35"/> Therefore in <hi>defiance,</hi> not of me; but of you, and your myſteries, and your now Romaine Catholick faith,<note place="margin">The refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſeruice of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed Maſſ. Latine Liturgie. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Saints. Praier for the dead. Conſecration of Bels, Books Candels, &amp;c. Elevation of hoſt. Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Croſſes.</note> They haue well and wiſely, and according to my will aboliſhed your ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable <hi>Maſſe and Mattens</hi> with the Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meries thereof; your ridiculous liturgie, and ſeruice in a ſtrange and vnknowne tongue, and therefore vnedifying; your ſuperſtitious <hi>Inuocation of Saints:</hi> your jrreligious <hi>prayer for the dead:</hi> your fooliſh and ſottiſh <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration,</hi> or coniuration rather of
<hi>Bells, Books, Candells,</hi> and ſuch like trifles and toyes; your thriſe jmpious and odious <hi>eleuation</hi> of a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer-god; iuſtlie offenſiue to euery good Chriſtian eye: Your ten-times jdolatrous profanation of Croſſing, and Croſſes; (at the ſight whereof (ſay you) <hi>the furies quake;</hi> Ah yee fooles:<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Homer. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> what furies meane you? thoſe fictions of the poets? nay: be they rather the raging furies of your owne diſtempered braines, and tormented Conſciences; as they may well enough; yee haue it in ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable vſe.<note place="margin">Images.</note> And ſo haue the pictures, and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages</hi> of ſaints, in your Temples, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and high waies: for which cauſe, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they may be to ſome, hiſtoricall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14468:35"/> and memorials of thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy perſonages, and <hi>leſſons of instruction to the Ignorant,</hi> to jmitate their vertues: yet other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,<note place="margin">quod legenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Scriptura hoc Idiotis praeſtat P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>crue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus. Greg. Rom. Epiſtolaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> ſeeing they can ſtirre vp nothing but a blind and buzzardly deuotion; and thoſe lay-mens bookes (as <hi>your Gregorie</hi> ſtiles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) can be no better then a doctrine of vanitie; though they be demoliſhed, <hi>broken, and burnt</hi> vpp, <hi>As Idolls;</hi> it is no matter: no more then that the ſigne of the Croſſe is vtterly aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and caſt away as it is in vſe,<note place="margin">Signe of the Croſſe not Popiſh hath a tolerable vſe. It is generally graunted euen by moſt learned diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinaricis. <hi>in immortalian la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o. Tertullian. Origen. Cyprian. See confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at Hampton Court an.</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4. <hi>Pag.</hi> 69.
<hi>Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ers. Mat.</hi> 5. Pſal. 116. Prou.
6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Veſtiments, and veſſels.</note> or abuſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther among you; howſoeuer they retayne it, as they finde it hath bin vſed in the prime &amp; purer Churches: yea at the ſacred Font. Now alſo; away with your ſmoky
<hi>tapers,</hi> &amp; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie candels, to giue you light at noone day; they are not able to enlighten you in your ſpirituall Darkenes. I Commaund: <hi>let your light ſo ſhine before men that they may ſee your good workes &amp;c.</hi> and to that purpoſe, let my <hi>word be a lanthorne vnto your feet and a light vnto</hi> yours pathes <hi>my Commaundement is a lanthorne, and Inſtruction a light.</hi> Let theſe other lights alone. <hi>Your Idle veſtments,</hi> and gay clothes, your <hi>veſsels</hi> alſo of your profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, put of: leaue of: and appeare no
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14468:36"/> more like heathniſh, or jewiſh prieſts in my preſence. And in a word: ſeeing this is all (as I perceiue) that you can except againſt the ſeruice of the Proteſtants: namely: becauſe they doe not communicate with your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh paltry traſh and Traditions, whereafter yee goe a whooring as after your owne jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions; let them alone to pray jnceſſantly <hi>for propagation</hi> of their reformed and pure profeſſion (no
<hi>Sect</hi> I-wiſſe:) againſt the Turke and Pope together; who are both, my profeſſed aduerſaries:<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.4.</note> the one raigning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, the other raging within my holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. No: your Pope is not <hi>Peters</hi> true and lawfull
<hi>Succeſsiour,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Pope hath forſaken the doctrine of Chriſt. His perſonall ſucceſſion could neuer yet be proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> either by doctrinall, or perſonall Succeſſion; much leſſe <hi>the Rocke of Faith.</hi> Finally; let their <hi>wals and pillers</hi> be ſtill more and more witneſſes of their jntegritie, and juſt departure from your, more then ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtious, apparently Idolatrous, abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations. And ſeeing their
<hi>miniſterie</hi> is the more ſacred vnto mee, the Leſſe agreement and conformitie it hath, and holdeth with your <hi>old,</hi> our rather new, vpſtart paltrie and patcherie; and their <hi>ſeruice</hi> I doe and will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge for mine owne: let your <hi>poore
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14468:36"/> Schiſmaticall ſoules</hi> (as yee terme them) joyne themſelues to my holy Sanctuaries. And I would not onely they, but all the reſt vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, that are mine, would ſpeedily make haſt, &amp; come out of your ſpirituall Sodome, <hi>Egypt,</hi> &amp; Babylon; Leaue your diſſimulation, or feare, or whatſoueer hindereth; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, not onely in part, but altogether ſuch, as are my faithfull Proteſtants. I ſay, Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them not to call them backe that are En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the <hi>old, and good way;</hi> but <hi>let my people goe, that they may ſerue me.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ierim. 6.16. Exod. 7.16.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>You can ſay that Priests did in many pariſhes follow the new courſe &amp;c.<note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly build vppon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And why rather leaue yee not vnto the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Biſhops. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Who vniuerſally died in long and lingring im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Oh but great preſidents moue you and many wiſe fellowes. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Where haue theſe Paſtors the key of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, whence fetch theſe Doctors their profound Learning?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14468:37"/>
                  <head>The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>BY this time you ſhould haue ended your pretended Meſſage: but I ſee, falſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors as yee are, what you cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force by Arguments, yee will attempt to perſwade by wordes. But haue you neuer read?<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Cor. 2.4.</note> 
                     <hi>not in the perſwaſiue words of mans wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome but in plaine euidence of the ſpirit and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</hi> Yf your <hi>Demy</hi>-Catholicks held an euill courſe, no reaſon they ſhould build vppon examples, either of <hi>pariſh Prieſts,</hi> or learned <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or any <hi>great preſidents,</hi> or any <hi>wiſe fellowes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nullum car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> exemplo neſas. Seneca.</note> or whatſoeuer <hi>Paſtors Doctors, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, or holy men.</hi> For which of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth not that no mans example is to be followed in ſin? But if <hi>Priests,</hi> and <hi>great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents,</hi> and <hi>wiſe fellowes, Paſtors,</hi> and <hi>Doctors;</hi> yea but <hi>puny ſtudents</hi> haue gon before them in a right way; to follow them it can be no fault, but a praiſe rather. Therefore vainely and Idly doe you make your compariſon betweene the <hi>pariſh Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>other preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,</hi> and
<hi>puny ſtudents</hi> on the one ſide as <hi>Corrupteſt ſoules, Carcaſes, Carions,</hi> &amp; the like; and the Biſhops whome you meane, great
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14468:37"/> (as you ſay) for <hi>learning,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Popiſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops neither ouer learned: neither vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kindly vſed by Q Elizab.</note> and <hi>ſuperiour functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> on the other. Eſpecially ſeeing thoſe bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops had no greater meaſure of learning, and ſanctity, then their great places; nor ſo much neither as their waightie functions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. But as for that jmpudent and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les lye which you are bold to vtter in my name of their <hi>Impriſonment &amp; death:</hi> I know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth to ſtand otherwiſe; jt is jntole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and hatefull in mine eares. For ſome of them were not jmpriſonned at all;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>See</hi> Tortura Torti. pag. <hi>146.</hi>
                     </note> ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the cuſtody of their honorable and louing friends: ſome after an eaſie jmpriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their ſtubbernnes to the Prince and States exiled themſelues: and onely Biſhop <hi>Bonner,</hi> that bloudy perſecutor of my Saints, died in the priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">A notable Popiſhlie and ſlaunder.</note> So vntrue it is that <hi>they died vniuerſally after long &amp; lingring impriſonment.</hi> Though had it bin ſo as you haue declared; yet their ſtubborn ſtanding out againſt the Truth had bin no good preſident for thoſe whome you blame, or any other, to refraine the companie or Communion of my Saints the Proteſtants.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:14468:38"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Examples fit to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</note>WHy rather fix ye not before your eyes ſo many &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Yf things preſent pleaſe you not caſt your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard vppon age? past &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>Examples yee bring, I ſee, of three ſortes' The firſt of your owne <hi>falſe Catholicks:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond of Certaine <hi>holy and</hi> good men, mencioned, ſome in the
<hi>Apocryphall,</hi> &amp; ſome in my <hi>Canonicall</hi> ſcriptures: The third of the
<hi>auncient Martyrs</hi> of the Church. To what end? forſooth, to perſwade further your
<hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> as yee call them, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe themſelues from the proteſtants ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and prayers. But neither is this any meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of mine vnto them. For firſt, the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the firſt ranke which you take and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge to bee the Martyrs and
<hi>Confeſſors</hi> of your owne Church; you miſtake, and miſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. You miſtake, For they were and are Traytors to their King and Country,<note place="margin">Traytors are Martyrs and Confeſſors, with Papiſts</note> diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all &amp; diſobedient Subiects to his Iuſt lawes; &amp; for their Treaſonable practiſes, manifeſt,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14468:38"/> and obſtinate breach of the Law; and not for the conſcience of their ſuperſtition, haue bin, and are according to iuſtice, yet with great mercy, both put to death, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonned. Yet are they <hi>not many; much</hi> leſſe <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes,</hi> in compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe valiant Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians whome the perſecuting Tyrants on your ſide haue murdered, jmpriſonned, and many waies afflicted,<note place="margin">In the raigne of Queene Mary Popiſh Tiranny.</note> in the ſpace of foure or fiue yeares Therefore theſe examples ought to haue bin ſpared in this place; as being miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applyed. For would you haue your Ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or
<hi>Ambidexter</hi> prieſts, to follow them in open profeſſion of their diſloyall practiſes againſt their naturall Prince and natyue Country? But the other of the ſecond order: viz. <hi>Tobias,</hi> the <hi>Iſraelits,</hi> the ſeauen <hi>Brethren, Eleazar, Maccabeus:</hi> alſo <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> &amp; Saint <hi>Iohn;</hi> are indeed, in themſelues the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable, and worthiof all jmitarion: But yet of them, who are ſure they maintayne the truth of god, as thoſe were, and did: not of your Pope-lings though yee bee ſtout, much leſſe when yee be ſtammering in your opinions. For what, ſay yee, what would
<hi>Tobias?</hi> what would the <hi>Iſraelites?</hi> what the 7.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14468:39"/> 
                     <hi>Brethren?</hi> what would <hi>Eleazar?</hi> what <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabeus?</hi> what would <hi>Peter?</hi> what <hi>Paul?</hi> or my beloued <hi>Iohn</hi> haue done in theſe times? would they not haue joyned with my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts? I ſay, yes; they would: and I am ſure, <hi>You</hi> they would haue <hi>deſpiſed, abhorred, reiected;</hi> and all your Babyloniſh jmpieties, and Profanations; no leſſe then they did the heathen perſecutors, Blud-ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers &amp; jdolaters of their time; and then they did thoſe named Hereticks <hi>Simon Magus, Ely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> and all the like, with their heathniſh jdolatries and deteſtable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies. But here I haue ſomewhat againſt you. Will you neuer clenſe your filthy tongues? neuer ceaſe to reuile, and rayle at my faithfull ſeruants, and worthy Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of my truth?<note place="margin">Luther.</note> What? is <hi>Luther</hi> like to
<hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus?</hi> no. But I muſt tell you: That <hi>man of ſinne</hi> who brags and vaunts him ſelfe to be an vniuerſall Biſhop in Simon Peters place, and is not; to be the Vicar generall of the vniuerſall Church on earth, and by me was neuer appointed to that office, is a very ſubtill Simon, and a Magicall enchaunter of my people. For I neuer gaue to my beloued
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14468:39"/> Apoſtle Simon Peter him ſelfe any ſuch place or power as this your Peter Pope by many crafty ſleights and deuiliſh practices hath aduanced himſelfe vnto. <hi>Luther? foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Grandfather of many falſehoods?</hi> No: No: but ordained of old, and borne, by my great prouidence and mercy, to be the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerer of your falſehoods, and recouerer, &amp; finder out of that holy truth which long had bin loſt in the ground, and dung of your Canoniſticall and Sophiſticall diuinitie; and many other of your meet machiauellianly politicall and practicall corruptions. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you hate him the more deadly; and I loue him the more dearely; and will loue &amp; honour him in my heauenly Kingdome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally. Dare you ſay of
<hi>Iohn Caluin?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Caluin.</note> (An Arch-<hi>Haeretick and corrupter of whole Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi>) whome though I know to haue <hi>knowne</hi> the truth <hi>in part,</hi> and
<hi>to haue prophecied in part,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.9.</note> as all my Seruants do: yet I haue well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued for a choyce Teacher and Inſtructor of the truth, by his laborious writings &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly jnſtitutions through all the parts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome? I ſay therefore once more: <hi>touch not mine Annoynted, &amp; do my prophets no harme:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 105.5.</note>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:14468:40"/> make not the Miniſters of my goſpell the ſeducers of ſoules;<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.16.</note> for <hi>they ſhall ſaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and them that heare them.</hi> Els I will come againſt you ſhortly and not <hi>onely conſume you with the breath</hi> of <hi>my mouth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.8.</note> but <hi>vtterly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh you by the brightneſse of my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming.</hi> Then ſhall you ſee and know the third ſort of your examples, myne Ancient true Martyrs, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy jndeed, of all jmitation for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant labouring, and ſtriuing in defence of my goſpell vnto the death, to be none of your defiled and corrupted Church: yea you ſhall ſee them, I ſay, Crowned with jmmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall happines and glory, but your ſelues with a number of falſe Martyrs whome yee haue thruſt into your yerely Kalender, with all haereticks and jdolaters, to be caſt out into <hi>vtter Darknes:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4.51.</note> 
                     <hi>there ſhalbe weeping and gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of teeth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23. &amp;. 24."/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in works of Haereſie worſe then in Acts of Idolatry.</note>IF now you be ſo ſimple as to thinke that Hereſie is not worſe then Idolatry that to forſake me &amp;c. Greater ſacriledge then the courteſie of Cap and Knee &amp;c. Euery Iote of whoſe rituall Cus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:14468:40"/>
                  <hi>24.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">24. Hereſie worſe then jnfidelity &amp; jdolatry.</note> Seeing euery falſhood the more it hath of truth is the more apt to beguile &amp;c.</p>
               <p>A plaine fable is laughed at but not hated &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23. &amp;. 24."/> The Lord Christ.</head>
                  <p>WHether Haereſie be worſe then Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry or no, I do not reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with you; neither is it to the purpoſe here. They are both Abhominable in my ſight: and damnable it is to communicate with ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But this is your perpetuall error, to take the Proteſtants for Haereticks: reforme that, and this declaration is altogether jmperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. Let <hi>Haereſie</hi> be worſe then
<hi>Infidelitie</hi> and <hi>Idolatry;</hi> yet if the profeſſed Proteſtants of England be not Haereticks, and their ſeruice not haereticall, you haue no Reaſon by that reaſon to call thoſe your adhaerents in ſome opinions from thoſe their Congregations, where they may learne to reforme them. but yee ſay: <hi>if yee be ſo ſimple as to thinke that to caſt</hi> 2.
<hi>or</hi> 3. <hi>graines of frankincenſe vppon an heathen Altar or to lay &amp;c. (that is) to offer, and doe homage to the Idols of the heathen. (Bacchus, Ceres, Iupiter,</hi> and the like:) to be <hi>greater ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14468:41"/> then the curteſie of Cap and knee and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerentiall preſence at their thrice Idolatrous Communion; or then the ſeruice to maintenaunce thereof erected, Euery iot of whoſe rituall Cus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes and publique prayers was inuented, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, practiſed, and is ſtill continewed, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in deteſtation, defiance, extirpation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of my faith Catholick: Then, oh then, how are yee deceaued?</hi> Firſt; why ſay you <hi>thriſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous</hi> Communion, and not rather <hi>thriſe haereticall</hi> in this place? being now about to Call your fellowes from the Haereſie of the Church of England: by preſuming the ſame to be worſe then Infidelitie &amp; idolatry? But this Crazines in your braine I forgiue you; only I would haue you ſhew but one poynt of Idolatry in that Communion.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> There is no worſhip of bread, as in yours: no venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no adoration of a croſſe or Crucifixe. They onely kneele, and do reuerence to me the honourable ſonne of God, repreſented vnto their faith, when they receaue the bread and wine in remembraunce of my death and paſſion.<note place="margin">§. 20. pag. 36. lin. 11.</note> Againe haue yee ſo ſhort and ſhitlie a memorie as to forget what you lately char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Proteſtant Church withall (viz.)
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14468:41"/> That their miniſterie hath ſtolen away <hi>your Churches ornaments;</hi> and <hi>let vp and downe clad in her robes?</hi> that now you ſay <hi>(euery lot of their rituall Cuſtomes, and publique prayers was inuented, Commaunded, practiſed, and is ſtill continewed onely in deteſtation, defiance, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation, and deniall of your faith Catholick?)</hi> for myne you call it falſely.) for if <hi>euery Iot</hi> of their rituall cuſtomes and publique pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers were inuented <hi>onely in deniall of your faith;</hi> then haue they <hi>stolen</hi> away none of your or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, nor <hi>let vp and downe</hi> in her robes &amp;c.: And if they haue ſtolen any, then eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Iot</hi> of their <hi>rituall Cuſtomes,</hi> was not inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as yee ſay. Thus jnconſequently and gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to ſpeake, is this to bring a meſſage from Heauen jn my name? Now Fie vppon ſuch folly.<note place="margin">Idolatrie and Haereſy are both alike ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable. It is Idle to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue which is the worſe.</note> Yf I ſhould examine your doughty Arguments, whereby yee would make jdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry a leſſe ſinne then haereſie; then, oh then, how ſhould you be confounded? for what a wordy Difference is this? that <hi>Haereſie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaks me; Idolatry neuer followed me:</hi> that <hi>deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me;</hi> this <hi>not confeſſeth me:</hi> that
<hi>abiureth me;</hi> this <hi>not knoweth mee:</hi> that <hi>blaſphemeth me;</hi> this not
<hi>honoureth me?</hi> A Diſtinction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14468:42"/> a difference. Who knoweth not but that jdolatry forſaketh, denieth, abiureth, and blaſphemeth me Alſo? ſayd I not of old vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Iſraell, <hi>they haue forſaken me the fountayne of Living Water &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 2.13.</note>) that fell into jdolatry not onely haereſie:<note place="margin">Do yee not confeſſe pag. 50. that I ſpake of all.</note> ſpake I not of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolators as well as of Haeretiks <hi>whoſoeuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth me before men &amp;c.</hi> Do not all Apoſtates from my truth,) whether into Haereſie or j<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, both abiure me, and blaſpheme me? Againe, doe not both ſorts fall away, ſome of jgnorance and ſimplicitie, ſome of Malice and contumacie? &amp; ſo both are bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten accordingly; ſometimes with few, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes with many ſtripes? And what a word is this? that <hi>to offer vnto Bacchus, and Ceres, and to moue the bonnet before Iupiter,</hi> is no greater ſacrilege then reuerendly to worſhip in my holy Temple? But yee bring a mayne rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.<note place="margin">Sect.
24.</note> 
                     <hi>Euery falſhood the more it hath of truth, is the more apt to beguile: the more apt to beguile</hi> the more <hi>pernicious to the Destruction of ſoules, and more abhominable.</hi> Therefore Haereſie, is worſe then Idolatry. Now I will make ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Euery falſhoode the leſſe it hath of truth: ſpecially if it haue none at all, the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14468:42"/> it is from me, <hi>(The way, the truth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh
14.6.</note> 
                     <hi>and the life):</hi> the farther it is from me; the neerer to the deſtruction of ſoules; and ſo Idolatry is worſe then Haereſie. Thus: be it that haereſie is in one reſpect; yet jdolatry is worſe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſo that the compariſon between them muſt needes be altogether fruitles and friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in this place. Specially in reſpect of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, who are no Haereticks, and who are Charged by you throughout this whole falſe Meſſage for Haereticks, jnfidels, and jdola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Your idle jlluſtrations, and Impertinent examples in this place, doe they proue Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie to be worſe than jdolatry, as they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended? Your firſt Illuſtration is: <hi>Falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which crye (the Lord, the Lord;) when I the Lord haue not ſpoken vnto them, are worſe ten-fold then the prophets of Baal)</hi> no, they are both alike Abhominable vnto me.<note place="margin">Luc. 19.14.</note> But <hi>out of thine owne mouth will I Iudge thee, thou euill ſeruant:</hi> For I the Lord haue not ſpoken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee this Embaſſage, yet haſt thou cryed in my name. Your ſecond: <hi>(Sooner ſhall the Publican be iuſtified then the Hypocriticall Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe)</hi> ſure the one ſhalbe juſtified by his Faith and repentance; and the other Condemned
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14468:43"/> for his pride and Hypocriſie. But what is that to this purpoſe? Your Third: <hi>(The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron-like adultres is more vile and hatefull before me the Lord, and men, then the open strumpet)</hi> Truth: the Matron is a more Cunning <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrit,</hi> but the ſtrumpet the more impudent whoore. They are both odious in my ſight: but the ſtrumpet is much more ſcandalous &amp; offenſiue, howſoeuer hatefull vnto men. Now, if ſhe be: the more intolerable ſhal it be for your Pope and Romane Church to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vnto me at the day of Iudgement for the maintenance of ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Stews. Your <hi>Fourth: A plaine Fable is laughed at, but not hated, becauſe it is not made to deceaue).</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lib. Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum. B. Franc.</note> yes the Fable of <hi>Saint Francis</hi> and the wolfe of <hi>Eugubium:</hi> and how the Freer rubbed out of his ſhinne a great ſpider which he had drunke in the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, without hauing any hurt: The fable of <hi>Saint Dennis</hi> that carried his own head in his hand two miles: The fable of your Lady of Hales how ſhe cured many ſickneſſes; and raiſed 7. perſons from the dead; &amp; did more Miracles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I the Sauiour my ſelfe, ſo juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Iuſtus <hi>Lipſius</hi> in the vneue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> balla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his vniuſt &amp; fooliſh Iudgement;<note place="margin">Iuſti Lipſij Diua.</note> and many
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14468:43"/> the like in your leaden <hi>Legend,</hi> that Fardel:<note place="margin">Legend.</note> of Fables, are both laughed at, hated, and made to deceaue; and if they were not, yet are apt to deceit whether the Author will or no. To be ſhort:<note place="margin">Georg. Fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius. approbat. Legend. Lipſij.</note> jt is a generall tale in pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that God giues power, not onely to Saints, but to their jmages and Pictures to worke wonders, both <hi>derided, hated, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented to deceaue.</hi> You adde: <hi>(But a lye forged and obtruded for a truth is intolerable.)</hi> ſo it is. and therefore ſo is this your lying Meſſage in my name, which here you deliuer vnto your Catholiks whoe hold conformitie with the Proteſtants. Finally; what ſpeake yee of the Chriſtians in <hi>Greece</hi> and
<hi>Africa</hi> againſt the <hi>Arrians?</hi> your <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> are farr vnlike the one, both in practiſe and in opinions: and yee your ſelues too to much reſemble the other. Your jdle nominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Martyrs and Confeſſors ſerueth not your turne at this time. In a word; in that you reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, &amp; commend againe your Traiterous crew to the jmitation of your Conformitans; it is a token of a ſhort memory, hauing done it ſo lately; and of much leſſe Grace, in doing it ſtill ſo lewdly.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:14468:44"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">By what commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God going to the Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</note>HOw Iuſt cauſe haue I then to exclame againſt you (Oh diſloyall wretches) how long will yee reiect my authoritie and kick againſt my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Or will you violently make me to meane before Iews and Heathen but not before Hereticks. &amp;c. Haue I not ſaid I am a iealous God. &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>ANd what needeth this? ſeeing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants are no Haereticks jn my ſight howſoeuer yee papiſts account them ſo, yea, as <hi>worſe then heathens and Infidels.</hi> Therefore you manifeſtly wrong theſe your fellow Papiſts that go to their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to challenge them in my name, for the breach of that great and maine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the abridgement of the whole lawe:<note place="margin">Deut. 6.5.</note> viz. <hi>That a man loue me with all his hart, with all his strength, with all his ſoule.</hi>) or of that particular charge in the ghoſpell <hi>(to be) leeue in heart</hi> &amp; <hi>alſo profeſſe beleefe before men-</hi> and alſo <hi>(he which denieth me before men ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be denyed of me in the preſence of Angels.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 10.32, 33.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 12.9.</note> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14468:44"/> I mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it of haereticks as well as of jewes &amp; heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. What then? do they therfore of your Popiſh opinions who goe to Protes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Churches deny me before Haereticks? that is your owne concluſion and not mine. In a word: I haue ſaid,<note place="margin">Eſay.
24.8.</note> 
                     <hi>(I will not giue my glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to another.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 7.5.</note>) I did ſeuerally forbid <hi>my people Iſraell</hi> to <hi>entermedle in Heathniſh rites:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exo. 23.31.32.</note> I did interdict them <hi>all ſocietie and conuerſation with Infidels:</hi> I did denounce by myne Apoſtles pen,<note place="margin">Rom.
10.9.</note> 
                     <hi>That as in heart men are to beleeue to Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, ſo with mouth they are to confeſse to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</hi> But they giue not my glory to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that goe to Proteſtant Churches: yee doo; that adore and worſhip jmages, Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and crucifixes. The rites of Proteſtants are not heathniſh, but few, and eaſie, and ſignifica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; yours of the Romane Synagogue, are borrowed both from Iewes, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens; (as I haue told you before); and a mightie multitude, both Idle and cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, for nomber and for nature. Their Conuerſation that haue ſociety with Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Proteſtants, js with faithfull Chriſtians: yours that are Romaine Catholicks, is with <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and his adhaerents. Now then I
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14468:45"/> commaund and Charge you all the ſort of you,<note place="margin">Chriſt Ieſus calleth not the wauering Romaine ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks from the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Churches &amp; Companies.</note> to ſpeake no more to your fellow Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks after this faſhion in my name. For I the Lord the omnipotent Creator haue not thus called them from among the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. But I exhort and warne them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to follow their faith: becauſe it is the faith of truth: that faith alſo to beleeue in heart, that they may be juſtified: and that Faith to Confeſſe with mouth, that they may be ſaued. As for you, you proud fleſh and bloud, neuer caſt vpp an jdle and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous accompt <hi>of merit added vnto me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits;</hi> yours, or theirs, or any mans to mine: which will neuer, verely I ſay vnto you, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to any ſume of Felicitie: mine owne beeing onely, and altogether al-ſufficient to that purpoſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the law of nature by going to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches.</note>And what if I had not in ſuch expreſse wiſe preſcribed your duty doth not the light of reaſon, the Law af nature &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Which faileth or falleth in one point of faith be fully guilty of Infidelitie &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:14468:45"/>
                  <head>The Lord Chriſt.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/>
                  </head>
                  <p>NO it doth not teach your Catholicks who are with Proteſtants any ſuch thing: viz. to
<hi>cleaue firmly to their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh faith</hi> and Religion; for that is ſtubbernly to perſiſt in error, and to embrace in deed <hi>a ſtrange and falſe faith,</hi> and
<hi>irreligious procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</hi> But what one argument bring you to proue that the <hi>lawe of Nature</hi> herein is vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated? Are you ſo jmpudent to alleage Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions in my name and bring no proofe at all? or do you goe about to prooue it thus? <hi>(He which breaketh one Commaundement is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of all, and a violater of Charitie: ergo hee which faileth or faulteth in one point of Faith is fully guilty of Infidelitie:</hi> and ſo by conſequent <hi>violateth the lawe of nature.</hi> The firſt aſſerſion I graunt is mine owne in myne Apoſtle;<note place="margin">Iam. 2.10.</note> if you vnderſtand it aright. But this latter, thus inferred, is your paradox. For if (he which faileth or faulteth in one point of faith be fullie guilty of jnfidelity, that is, muſt needs be charged and taken for a meer jnfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del: then not onely all haereticks and you Papiſts; who faile in many poynts of Faith;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14468:46"/> but euen all true Chriſtians, and good Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks muſt be condemned ſo to:<note place="margin">Cor. 13 9.</note> ſeeing they <hi>all know but in part;</hi> and
<hi>propheſie in part:</hi> and ſo muſt needs faile in one point of Faith at leaſt, euen that which is hidden from their knowledge whereto they cannot for that cauſe yeld any manner of aſſent: no man conſenting vnto that which in his knowledge he doth not apprehend at all. And thus ye Condemne by this Paradox all the world; and namely, all Chriſtendome; and your owne Romane Church, for jnfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels: nay; fully guiltye of jnfidelitie: and ſo there are no beleeuers at all by your doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine: There is no Church, no Faith, No Truth, no Goſpell, no Chriſt, no God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men. Heere I muſt tell you alſo. Though in ſome ſence hee that is fully guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of jnfidelitie, that is, that beleeueth no one poynt at all of god or godlines, as he ought;<note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> 
                     <hi>his very minde and Conſcience is defiled:</hi> and ſo the light of reaſon, and the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is violated in him: Yet thoſe famous and Renowned
<hi>Paragons,</hi> among the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. <hi>Triſmegiſtus; Pythagoras; Socrates; &amp;c. Cato, Ariſtides, Scipio,</hi> and many others of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14468:46"/> that ranck, for their great and Admirable learning, profound politick wiſedome, and worthy morall vertues, were neuer-theleſſe verie great lights; and had the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon ſhining in them gloriouſly, concerning many ſecular and ciuill affaires, and liued in many things agreeable to the lawe of Nature. How be it, concerning Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and heauenly things, yea, the true knowledge of God <hi>they became vaine in their Imaginations,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 1.21.</note> 
                     <hi>and their fooliſh hearts where full of Darknes,</hi> and in that might they be ſayd to be fully guilty of jnfidelity; becauſe they knew not God the Father in me his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> So that,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.18. &amp;. 26.8.9.10. &amp;. 17.3.</note> ſome may be fully guilty of jnfidelitye; and yet not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate the law of Nature. Wherfore be not ſo raſh hereafter, I aduiſe you, to proiect your Paradoxes in my name: do not challenge them for partaking with haereticks that goe to proteſtants: neither ſay any more that your Church, your Faith, your Sacraments, are myne, as ye doe. For I will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them: yee doe me jniurie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:14468:47"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hereſie &amp; perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God for tryall of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hearts.</note>I Foretold while I conuerſed on earth that he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies of neceſsitie muſt be for the triall &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> The Lord Christ.</head>
                  <p>True it is, <hi>I foretold of Haereſies for the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of my Saints.</hi> But are ye Romaniſts therefore the vniuerſall Church? No. yee know and allow my ſeruant
<hi>Auſten</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the Donatiſts of his time:<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note>
                     <hi>Africa non eſt orbis.</hi> Therefore I ſay alſo vnto you: The Synagogue of Rome is not the <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Church.</hi> And do Proteſtants and their followers <hi>preferre their owne Imaginations</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it? I tell you, nay; but yee Papiſts doe; and run a madding after your owne jnuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Apoſtaticall Traditions, cloſed and claſped vp in the boſome of your Pope.<note place="margin">Luc. 12.51.</note> What though I forwarned; <hi>that I came not to ſend peace but ſeparation;</hi> (meaning) not that I doe loue, or bring diuiſion and ſtrife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men; but that many, whoſe hearts my ſelfe haue not reformed, are, and wilbe euer ſo bad and obſtinate in their euill opinions and wicked wayes, wilfully diſobeying my
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14468:47"/> Ghoſpell, that they will gaine ſay and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their owne parents,
<hi>Children, Princes, Subiects, Maiſters, Seruants, wiues, Huſbands, Brethren, Kinſfolks,</hi> and <hi>Friends</hi> that profeſſe my name; yea and will raiſe vp bitter
<hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> againſt them. But I had no meaning to teach Children, or ſeruants or Wiues, or Brethren, or friends, diſobedience and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty againſt their Parents, theyr Maiſters, their Huſbands, their Brethren, their frinds; much leſſe to foſter treaſons in a ſtate, to raiſe vp mutinies and rebellions, to arme naturall ſubiects againſt their naturall Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to practiſe the ouerthrowe of their Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, for the pretended catholick cauſe. Theſe are diabolicall ſuggeſtions, and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Sathan my ſworne Enemie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with yee Romaniſts are too too much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>ARe yee Christians and think your ſelues excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the precept &amp;c.<note place="margin">Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Reuealed you are to your owne ſhame and to my griefe. &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:14468:48"/>
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>DIſſimulation and double dealing I hate in euery thing: and in acts of Religion I vtterly abhorre you need not proue it by the Prohibitions in the law;<note place="margin">Deut. 22
10.11.</note> 
                     <hi>of wearing a garment of linſey woolſey, ploughing with an Oxe &amp; an Aſse, ſowing a field with diuers kind of ſeeds;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 10.9.</note> or by the parable of <hi>Salomon. He that walketh vprightly walketh ſafely, or boldly.</hi> But will yee then remember how I cannot but deteſt your popiſh aequiuocation, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall reſeruation? which is nothing elſe but flat lying &amp; hypocriſie. As for thoſe of your popiſh opinions which conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto the Proteſtants, herein they muſt needs offend me, in that they beleeue with you, and profeſſe with them: for I would haue them not only profeſſe as they doe, but alſo change their Faith: as long as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the doctrine of your Antichriſtian Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, me they cannot pleaſe. For as they are Chriſtians and know full well that my Commaundement,<note place="margin">Deut. 13.1.</note> 
                     <hi>(not to hearken vnto a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauer,)</hi> belongeth vnto all: ſo my wil is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they ſhould take knowledge, how
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14468:48"/> that you Papiſts are the falſe-prophets of theſe times, who compaſſe ſea and land to make one proſelyte, and to draw as many as you can vnto that <hi>new, ſtrange,</hi> and <hi>falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of your romiſh faith; vſing all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and diabolicall crafts you can, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the diuell himſelfe the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſer of the earth, either to perſwade,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.7.</note> or elſe to enforce them to fall downe and worſhip the whoore, the beaſt, and the falſe prophet,<note place="margin">Apoc.
19.20.</note> and him only to ſerue; I ſay, euen that new, and ſtrange abhominable Idoll,<note place="margin">An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e. Eudae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. pro Hen. Garnet. pag. <hi>137.</hi> &amp; <hi>138.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>the Lord your God the Pope,</hi> of which Title and Blaſphemy ſome of you are now aſhamed. As touching the doctrine of the Proteſtants: ſhew in what one point it is not ancient, and Apoſtolicall that you call it new. They tell you, and haue prooued it oft vnto you;<note place="margin">Popiſh new doctrines</note> that your Canon &amp; Idoll of the Maſſe, your Carnall preſence, and tranſubſtantiation in the holy Supper: your interdiction of the Cup to the Laitie: your adding of ſalt, and ſpittle, oyle, and creame in the Ceremonie of Baptiſme; and many other points of your beleefe, where neuer heard of in myne Apoſtles times, or in many yeares after. But ye exclame and cry
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14468:49"/> out vppon them, <hi>new Doctrine; new Faith; new Ghoſpell:</hi> yet are yee not able to ſay and prooue it of any point thereof: <hi>This is new.</hi> How is it then that you are ſo <hi>malapert</hi> with my Ghoſpell, and the truth of chriſtianitye which they profeſſe, to begin the originall thereof both fooliſhly and falſely, ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly,<note place="margin">Luther. Caluin.</note> and blaſphemouſly from <hi>Mart. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Caluin?</hi> Remowned and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Inſtruments of my glory they were in their time; and valiant oppugners and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnators of your Antichriſtian haeraeſies: But no firſt <hi>founders,</hi> or <hi>Authors,</hi> of my aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall truth and ghoſpell. Moreouer,
<hi>Caluins Idoll?</hi> who? or what is that I pray you? (The Popes Idoll is the Maſſe:) And which are <hi>the Calamities of this preſent tyme</hi> whereof yee prate. The hand of Iuſtice is to remiſſe and ouerſlack vppon you, as appeareth, in that you are ſo bold to ſpeake, and write, and print your paltry Pamphlets, and ſeditious Libels at your pleaſure. Wherfore neuer tel your ſuppoſed Schiſmaticks, that, <hi>They are reuealed to their owne ſhame and to my griefe:)</hi> neither Call vppon them any more to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe your Faith by <hi>a conuerſation pleaſing</hi> you:
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14468:49"/> but learne your ſelues at length, to profes Syncerely the true faith by a godly life; or I will make it ſhortly knowne to all the world to your owne perpetuall ſhame and horror, that yee are the men who haue greiued and vexed me with your calumnious exclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt my Saints, and jdolatrous ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations againſt my ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>ADmit that neither reaſon nor rule of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſuggeſted vnto you:<note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the authoritie of the Church.</note> nor that I expreſly exacted of you ſuch firme confeſſion of faith: yet ought not the authoritie of my Church, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Nor to my Vicar on earth &amp;c. The decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of my generall Councell at Trent &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> The Lord Christ.</head>
                  <p>WHat a doe is here? will ye neuer giue ouer railing, and ſlaunder? how long ſhall I ſuffer you? Oh yee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient and jmpudent <hi>Generation?</hi> I tell you againe: your
<hi>Church,</hi> your <hi>Prieſts,</hi> your <hi>Vicar,</hi> your <hi>Councell at Trent,</hi> are none of mine: I renounce you all: your Church, for
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14468:50"/> the Synagogue of Sathan: your prieſts, for the miniſters of
<hi>Beliall:</hi> your Vicar, for a deceaver, an jdolater, a grand falſe Prophet, as
<hi>Balaam:</hi> your councell at Trent, for a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conventicle of Popiſh Prelats and Prieſts of your owne faction. Fooliſhly then and ridiculouſly doe you charge your Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks of contempt of <hi>my Church, my Spouſes voyce</hi> and admonition; Madly doe you cenſure them for <hi>worſe then Heathens and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels;</hi> and diveliſhly do you accurſe them all. It is jndeed <hi>as ſacrilegious as Idolatry</hi> to obay your Church; to enter
<hi>your haereticall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles;</hi> to giue external conſent to <hi>your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable rites.</hi> But to frequent the ſervice of the Proteſtant Churches, the Eccleſiaſticall aſſemblies of my true Saints, is ſo well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto me; that had theſe harkned vnto your Prieſts who called them there-from, I ſhould haue held it grieuous ſacriledge by conſent betweene them both; had they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayned, and refuſed the pardon of life vpon ſo godly a condition; (viz:) to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with my Church of <hi>England:</hi> I ſhould haue found them guilty of their own bloud; as now I doe theſe Prieſts. I had a godly
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14468:50"/> Biſhop that gaue them a godly rule,<note place="margin">Augus. Dulci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio. ep.
<hi>61.</hi> Jdem. ad. Fes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. ep <hi>167.</hi>
                     </note> if they had had the grace to haue kept it.
<hi>Cauſa non paenafacit Martyrem,</hi> the cauſe not the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment maketh the Martyr: And my ſelfe haue pronounced them bleſſed that ſuffer, But,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.
5.10.</hi> Addidit mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam quae vera Sacrilegio pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas Sec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Aug. cont. ep. Permeniani. lib. <hi>1.
1.</hi> Reg. <hi>18.28.</hi> Santons. Hagies.</note> 
                     <hi>propter Iuſtitiam,</hi> in a righteous cauſe, or for righteouſnes ſake. But tell mee now: how farr vnlike herein were theſe your Papiſts to the Prieſts of <hi>Baall,</hi> that cut and launced their bodies? and thoſe phantaſticall <hi>Santons</hi> or <hi>Hagies,</hi> (as they call them) among the Turks and Moores, that diſoculate, and wound, and even kill themſelues in the madnes of their Superſtition? Alſo, I know, I know: your Pope (not my Vicar) is after a faſhion ſo
<hi>ſolicitous for ſoules</hi> that hee ſpareth neither care nor coſt; yet not to ſaue them, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and murther them: ſo that hee moſt aptly reſembleth even Sathan himſelfe, the great compaſſer of the Earth: as his jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal vaſals alſo doe thoſe their famous Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, the Phariſees;<note place="margin">Mat. 23.15.</note> 
                     <hi>that compaſsed both Sea and Land to make one Proſelyte,</hi> and having made him, transforme him two-fold more the child of Hell then they themſelues are. What doe I? or what ſhould any of my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14468:51"/> reſpect, what your Tridentine aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly decreed againſt them? They were blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Haereticks</hi> themſelues; and they had all and every one the marke of the beaſt in their foreheads.<note place="margin">Prov. 26.2.</note> As for their <hi>Anathema: The curſe that is cauſeles ſhall not come;</hi> for of my faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Proteſtants I ſtill pronounce: <hi>Bleſsed is he that bleſſeth them, and curſed be he that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Haereticks how pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely to be ſhunned.</note>BEſides that principall praecept of louing God aboue all, &amp;c. If you will but a little looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you, ye ſhall find that I haue yet left you ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commandement, &amp;c. Well then, whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit but mine inſpired and eſtabliſhed as a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all obſeruation to the worlds end, that Haereticks, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>WHat an jdle Expoſtulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is this? for it ſhall bee graunted vnto you <hi>that Haereticks ſhould be vtterly auoyded,</hi> as ſuch and ſuch whom you haue alleadged and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14468:51"/> deſcribed truely out of the ſcriptures. But that the Proteſtants are the Haereticks, and you the true Catholicks ſhall not be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. So that yee haue impertinently abuſed the ſcriptures. Wherefore ſpeake no more preſumptuouſly, let not arrogancy proceed out of your mouth. Not they that come to Proteſtants, but rather yee, that hold and hang with Papiſts, <hi>participate with Infidels; haue fellowſhip with Beliall,</hi> and <hi>the cup of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils; are in darkenes; Ioyne with Lucifer; come to the ſolemnitie of Babylon;</hi> make a bargaine <hi>with hell,</hi> and <hi>with accurſed Death;</hi> and that not ſo much for feare of any worldly loſſe or croſſe; <hi>as for affection to your ſinne.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I counſell you, repent and turne you, from your abhominations: elſe I will come againſt you ſhortly, and giue you your por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the whore, the beaſt, the falſe-prophet, and the Dragon, whome you ſerue: in the lake that burneth with fier and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone: <hi>the ſame is the ſecond death.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſy and not with pure ſchiſme on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>SHal they then which profeſse Haereſie with Haereticks be found cleare &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:14468:52"/>
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> The Lord Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>NOw the Schiſmaticks are infected with Haereſie: and of this you haue chalenged them long agoe. But thus you ſeeth and boyle your coleworts ouer, and againe, thus for lack of matter you fill an Idle and vngodly meſſage full of vaine and wicked words, charging, and challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, thundring and thretning, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as much as in you lieth, poore and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted ſeely ſoules into deſperation of my mercie for entring into the rightway. Thus did your father the Deuill deale with my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant M. <hi>Luther</hi> when I began to call him firſt from your Pauilions. For hee would needs perſwade him that he ſhoud bee dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Proteſtant profeſſion,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luther</hi> de Miſsa priuata</note> becauſe he had byn once a popiſh Prieſt, had ſayd Maſſ, had turned the <hi>Euchariſticall</hi> bread into my body, and done ſuch other like feats of your ſuperſtition; and now was revolted from it. How abſurdly and how jmpudently do you compare my true beleeuers in <hi>England</hi> to the
<hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> jnfidels? but that you haue a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to abuſe my word, and to miſapply
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14468:52"/> the ſcriptures. I will ſurely puniſh you for this thing. What
<hi>fire,</hi> or <hi>flame,</hi> or <hi>Sea-ſurges,</hi> or <hi>pitch</hi> is this you prate of? do not I know, yee erre, not knowing what you ſay? But let me ſee how learnedly and diuinely you prooue your ſuppoſed Schiſmaticks to bee Haereticks. Your learning is to ſay, and not to prooue. Your diuinitie was neuer foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on my word, but faſhioned and framed in your owne forge. For what are the Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies wherewith they are infected? forſooth <hi>(euery one almoſt (rarer is he then a white Crowe who doth it not) either cancelleth faſting daies by his owne Authoritie, or diſpenſeth with meats prohibited as often as he liſt; or doubteth of ſome Article of Faith, if not of all.</hi> What? do they cancell faſting daies? and which I pray you? I ſay, thoſe onely of your popiſh inſtitution. And how? jn that they faſt not after your popiſh faſhion. I wiſſe, a very great offence. <hi>I but of their owne Authoritie they doe it.</hi> No: They haue the Authoritie of the Lawfull Magiſtrate to beare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out. <hi>They diſpence with meats prohibited as often as they liſt)</hi> By the law of my eternall Ghoſpell ther are no meats prohibited. For doth not my Apoſtle
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14468:53"/> tell you?<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.4.5.</note> 
                     <hi>that euery Creature of God is good, and nothing ought to be refuſed if it be receaued with thanksgiuing; for it is ſanctified by the word of God and prayer.</hi> If then, (<hi>not as often as they list,</hi> that is your calumny:) but as often as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity requireth, and as they may without publique ſcandal or offence, they make no difference of meats; but vſe them all without ſcruple of Conſcience put betweene this and that: Oh ſure, it is a greeuous crime. It is jndeed, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g your ſuperſtitious orders: but not among my holy Saints; who haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that this your prohibition of meats pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the ſpirit of Error;<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.1.</note> and is a doctrine of Deuils. Are theſe your <hi>Haereſies?</hi> to cancell Popiſh faſting dais, &amp; eat of meats prohibited by the Church of Rome? But I ſay: theſe are actions croſſing the <hi>Haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> doctrine of your Antichriſtian Canons: they are no haereſies. Beſides, to <hi>doubt of this or that Article of faith,</hi> yea, <hi>of all the Articles of your faith;</hi> call you this jnfection of <hi>Haereſies?</hi> But I ſay: to diſſent from the moderne faith and doctrine of the Romane Church, and ſtoutly to maintaine the contrary, is not Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie in my ſight: much leſſe onely to doubt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14468:53"/> of any, or of all the articles thereof. For firſt, as many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as are different from the Proteſtant profeſſion, they are the erroneous articles of a falſe Church, a ſynagogue and conventicle jnfected with many haereſies. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if they were all granted to be true; yet ſeejng all Haereſie is a confirmed and ſetled error:<note place="margin">Haereſis error confirmatus. See Aug. cont. Creſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Gram.</note> and whoſoever doubteth is ever ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering as yet, vnſetled, and vnreſolved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doubteth: therefore hee that doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of whatſoever poynts, cannot bee ſayd fitly &amp; properly, either to be well affected to the truth, or to be jnfected with haereſie. why? becauſe hee ſtandeth jndifferent, and jrreſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute; though declining from the one; yet not as yet embracing, or jndeed, jnfected with the other. Nevertheleſſe, let it now be yeilded vnto you: that they who are not perfect Haereticks; yet may be jnfected with haereſies, or haereticall opinions: tell mee, what, and which they be, whereof you chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge theſe your Schiſmaticks? You ſay: <hi>One improoueth Confeſsion; another Purgatory; this man inuocation of Saints, or vſe of Images; that man prayers for the dead; or the office in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine;</hi> doubtles, a very greevous accuſation;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14468:54"/> and miraculous poynts of <hi>Haereſie.</hi> But will you neuer learne? that, your <hi>Auricular</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion <hi>in a Corner:</hi> your <hi>Pagan</hi> purgatory in an
<hi>vnknowne world:</hi> your <hi>praeſumtuous</hi> jnvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saints, vnder <hi>colour of humility:</hi> your <hi>Idolatrous vſe</hi> of jmages: your <hi>idle</hi> prayers for the dead
<hi>at reſt:</hi> your Latine office, and ſeruice in an <hi>vnknowne tongue:</hi> I, even I my ſelfe, haue ever jmprooued, repooued, and condemned? So haue I alſo them, that <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Antichriſt ſhall be</hi> one ſingular <hi>perſon,</hi> and not a ſucceſſion of many; becauſe they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſe my holy Revelation therein. Yet to ſuppoſe and belieue as I haue reuealed it to my ſervant <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 17.18.
<hi>alibi<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>.</hi>
                     </note> you will needs jmpute it for an infection of haereſie. Moreouer, you are not content with me, the true and onely <hi>head of the Church</hi> which is <hi>my body;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ephe 4.15.</note> and the preſence of my grace and power,<note place="margin">Mat.
28.20.</note> whereof I ſpake when I ſayd, <hi>Behold I am with you to the end of the world:</hi> But except there be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged one viſible, and miniſteriall Head; that your
<hi>Pope</hi> (forſooth) may be the man: and tirannize ouer the conſciences of my people; the very Antichriſt <hi>ſitting in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Theſ.
2.4.</note> 
                     <hi>and aduancing himſelfe aboue all that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14468:54"/> is called God:</hi> it muſt bee haereſie with you. But, come yee now, and reaſon with me of theſe poynts, if ye be able, if it bee poſſible that ye can bring any other Arguments then haue byn brought, and anſwered already by my ſervants: or elſe becauſe ye are not able, I jmpoſe you ſilence, and charge you hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth to ſet a broche no more lyes, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries in my name. For if yee doe; I will call you to accompt at my dreadfull day of Iudgement when ye ſhall not eſcape. The <hi>Councels</hi> of my primitiue Church are of good and great authority in their kind;<note place="margin">Your <hi>Gregor.</hi> was too bold ſo to compare them.</note> but not of the greateſt; not any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aequall to my 4.
<hi>Euangeliſts:</hi> your <hi>decrees Eccleſiaſticall</hi> of farr leſſ; as contayning in them many Cannons both erroneous, ridiculous, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous. The gates of Hell cannot prevaile againſt my Church; for I haue grounded it vppon <hi>a Rock,</hi> that is, <hi>my ſelfe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.4.</note> But your Church is not my Rock; as well appeareth: for the gates of hell haue already preuailed againſt it; and it hath loſt <hi>the ſpirit of truth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn. 14. ver. 16.26.</note> 
                     <hi>the promiſe of my Father;</hi> yea, the faithfull Citie,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.8.</note> 
                     <hi>whoſe faith was famous ſometimes in all the world:</hi> is become an harlot, like <hi>Samaria,</hi>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:14468:55"/> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> long agoe: and ſhe hath playd the harlot with all her neighbour Princes, whom ſhee could jntice. Therefore they doe well, and follow the truth in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that call in queſtion the authority of many Councels and aſſemblies of men; that detract from your Eccleſiaſtical decrees and decretals: that, not onely feare, but beleeue, and find; and report abroad; not, that I haue not fulfilled my promiſe,<note place="margin">Act. 2.1. &amp;c.</note> for I haue; <hi>and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ſent my ſpirit of truth the Comforter</hi> vnto my choſen, which ſhall lead them into all truth: but, that the ſame my ſpirit hath beene by you, your Praelats, and your falſe-teachers di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly abuſed, and deſpited; ſo that it hath byn preſſed, and as it were compelled to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake you, and depart from you many yeares agoe. Ceaſe ye then to caſt your filthie haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies vppon my Saints: or to call them backe into your ſtewes; whome I haue cauſed to come, and joyne, and dwell with them in my holie houſe. Els: thou <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> harlot; woe, wo, vnto thee? Ah, how ſhall I puniſh thee in the end? how ſhall I be avenged of thee? ſeeing thou doſt all theſe things of an jmpudent whooriſh woman.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:14468:55"/>
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> The falſe Embaſſador.</head>
               <p>WHence all this?<note place="margin">By what meanes Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks grow to be Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks.</note> not becauſe the longer yee liue &amp;c. By neuer talking with Prieſts, not conferring of matters touching the Spirit, by being loden &amp;c. As in domeſticall Adders and in their familiarity, as in Cocatrice eyes &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Flee Babilon, flee Chore, flee Sodome, flee from the aduerſarye campe in tyme. &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> The Lord Christ.</head>
                  <p>HEre againe, as els where, and almoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where in this falſe Embaſſage, you diue into the Conſciences of your brethren: and you can tell them, without me, yet very boldly in my name, that they begin to loth your religion, for checking of their humor. For you challenge them that <hi>feare of aduerſity; loue of the world; neuer tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with your Prieſts; nor conferring of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters touching the ſpirit; and the load of ſecret ſins;</hi> haue jnduced them to depart from among you. Thus you raile vpon them; exclaime; expoſtulate; advize; and commaund them in my name; reſtles as you are. You rayle vpon them <hi>as poſſeſsed of ſenſuall, carnall, and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14468:56"/> worldly affections. lying open to the enemy, deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of my grace and protection, made a prey to the roaring Lyon, conuerſing among haereticks, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming like them in conditions, quickly delighting in their ſutable doctrine.</hi> To which they can ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily anſwere if they bee wiſe, that thus haue you deciphered your own ſelues, ye Runna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates: who have forſaken a good and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant land, to converſe among your Romane Haereticks: and ſo are made like vnto them in evill and vngodly conditions: diſloyall to your Prince and country; having firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed your ſelues to their damnable doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. Therefore you are, as you ſay of them <hi>ſenſual, carnal, &amp; worldly affectionated, lying ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Enemy, deſtitute of the Sauiours grace and protection, and made a prey to the roaring Lyon.</hi> You exclame: <hi>poyſon, poyſon lurketh in their company;</hi> meaning the Proteſtants, you ſhould haue ment your ſelues, <hi>as in domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Adders, and in their familiaritie as in Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trices or Baſilisks eyes.</hi> Thus doe you plainly ſhew that Adders poyſon is in your lips; and vnder your tongue lurketh vngodlines and vanity. You expoſtulate: <hi>What though they be not conquered at the firſt? what though the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14468:56"/> of Proteſtants be but weake &amp; fooliſh? yet that they may in time be perſwaded &amp; ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e by them.</hi> So they may jndeed; for thoſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as weake and fooliſh as they are, yet you do find them <hi>Gordian</hi> knots, and like <hi>the Trumpets</hi> of the Prieſts of the Lord of Hoaſtes,<note place="margin">Ioſue. 6.20.</note> 
                     <hi>at the blaſt whereof the wals of Ieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co fell downe:</hi> yea, like <hi>ſtones in dauids bag;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.49.</note> whereof ſome one, or other, when the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of your wickednes is filled vp, ſhall ſtick ſo faſt in the forehead of <hi>your Pope, the great Goliah,</hi> that he ſhall fall groueling to the ground, and neuer be able to riſe againe. Then ſhall you find thoſe Arguments, which now are <hi>but drops of Raine,</hi> to fall v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon you as a ſtorme; as haileſtones, and Coles of fier. For ſure it is,<note place="margin">Eſay. 55.10.</note> as <hi>my word is like the ſnow and rayne which commeth downe from heauen, and watereth the Earth, that it may bud and bring forth, ſeed vnto the ſower, and bread vnto him that eateth;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 6.7.8.</note> 
                     <hi>ſo the earth that drinketh in the rayne which falleth oft vppon it, &amp; brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth nothing but bryers and thornes, is neer vnto Curſing, whoſe end is to be burned.</hi> Your vnſavoury compariſons of the <hi>ſmale worme,</hi> and <hi>contemptible Iuye,</hi> are more agreeable
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14468:57"/> vnto your ſelues; Such eating vermins are your Ieſuits, that neble at my goodly vyne: ſuch <hi>claſping Iuye,</hi> ſucking out the ſap of this my noble Plant, and Tree; which in my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of England myne owne right hand hath <hi>Planted, hedged, and defenced.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; as you counſell and commaund them in my name, ſo do I: with this onely diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: that not the Proteſtants, but you and your Church are in mine accompt the
<hi>Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks;</hi> the <hi>Babylon;</hi> the <hi>Korahs companie;</hi> and the <hi>Sodome:</hi>) And I would haue both them and you to know; that as I am the mightie God, and Sauiour of the world: ſo that all my counſels are commaunds. Among your ſelues, the ſonnes of men, yee haue a Rule; and men of wiſedome haue great regard vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. <hi>Potentiores cum rogant, iubent.</hi> And can you then jmagine, that whatſoeuer I aduize, muſt not carrie with it the force of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund? This then I ſay, and commaund vnto your <hi>Schiſmaticks; diſsembling papists; falſe-hearted catholicks, Hypocrits, weaklings, Newters,</hi> (terme them what yee will; be they as they are,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.1.</note>) to whome you haue directed this Embaſſage.
<hi>Beware of Dogs: beware of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:14468:57"/> euill workers. beware of the Conciſion.</hi> Flee the felowſhip of Romane Haereticks; be not jnfected with the leuen of their Doctrine; <hi>goe out of Babell;</hi> come out from amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them; <hi>be yee ſeparated, and touch no vncleane thing:</hi> no Idols; no ſhrines, no reliques, no wafer-gods: or the like: &amp; I will receaue you. Yf ye will not periſh in the error of <hi>Balaam;</hi> and the gaine-ſaying of <hi>Korah;</hi> if yee will come from Antichriſt, and his Adhaerents, myne Aduerſaries camp, and dwell among my Choſen, if yee will loue me, embrace and learne my true religion, which they profes,<note place="margin">2. Cor.
6.17.18.</note> 
                     <hi>I wilbe a Father vnto you, and yee ſhalbe my Sonnes and Daughters.</hi> I am the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Lords Concluſion.</head>
               <p>HEtherto, yee wicked Impes of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, I haue vouchſafed to lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad your folly, and jmpiety in your owne vaine; and even in mine owne words to controwle, and Counter-mand your falſe Embaſſage, and blaſphemous Meſſage; which you haue divulged as from my ſelfe.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14468:58"/> To the end that all the world may know how greatly I deteſt, how deeply I abhorr your whooriſh, and even deviliſh jmpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency; to abuſe my perſon, and breath out blaſphemies in my ſacred name. Now, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſee you reele, and tumble backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into your former accuſations, of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy, and jngratitude to God; of jmpug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Catholick Faith:<note place="margin">§ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.34.35.36. &amp;c.</note> of greiuouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing God: and in all the reſt of your decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, onely reaſon with them, how they can excuſe themſelues from this your jmpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of joyning with my true profeſſors; alleadging many colours, pretenſes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes (as ye ſuppoſe) of this their fact: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be guilty, or no; they are in this poynt wiſe, and able, and old enough, let them anſwere for themſelues. If they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere you ſyncerely, that the loue of truth hath drawne them herevnto, never blame them any more. For mine Apoſtle by my ſpirit hath commanded.<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.21. 1. Ioh. 4.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Try all, keepe the good.</hi> Another; <hi>Trie the Spirits, whether they be of God or no.</hi> Prouided alwayes that they be
<hi>not euer learning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.7</note> 
                  <hi>and neuer come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth.</hi> But if they do indeed, as
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:14468:58"/> you haue layd the load vpon their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, diſſemble only, (tell a time ſhall ſerue to vnmaſke themſelues) with me their God &amp; Lord: &amp; with the world. Alas, alas, are they ſuch fooles to walke in Darkenes in my ſight? For <hi>the Darknes is no Darkenes to me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.12.</note> 
                  <hi>the Darkenes and light to me are both alike.</hi> But: let them anſwere for themſelues, becauſe yee doe prouoke them: and I wilbe the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrator betweene you both. For I will ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Iudge both them, and you, and all the world,<note place="margin">Iu. ep. verſ. 14 15.</note> at mine jlluſtrious Apparition in the Clouds: <hi>when I ſhall come with Thouſands of my Saints;</hi> and I will giue ſentence
<hi>againſt all men;</hi> and will take vengeance, and rebuke <hi>all the vngodly</hi> among them, <hi>of all their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deeds which</hi> they haue vngodly commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>and of all their cruell ſpeakings,</hi> which wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſinners haue ſpoken againſt me.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14468:59"/>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Jgnatius epiſt. 6. ad Philadel.</note>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Brethren, be not deceiued: if any man fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him that deuideth him-ſelfe from the truth he ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of God. And yf any man withdraw not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from a falſe teaching or a lying Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, he ſhall be condemned into Hell. For neither ought we to depart from the godly; neither to haue conuerſation with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
